<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certaine godly and verie comfortable letters, full of christian consolation. Written by M. Ed Dering vnto sondry of his friends. And nowe published, for the proffite of the Church of God</title>
            <author>Dering, Edward, 1540?-1576.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1590</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 115 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B12393</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 6682.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116582</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851798</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851798</idno>
            <idno type="VID">178438</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B12393)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 178438)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1304:4, 1685:2c)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certaine godly and verie comfortable letters, full of christian consolation. Written by M. Ed Dering vnto sondry of his friends. And nowe published, for the proffite of the Church of God</title>
                  <author>Dering, Edward, 1540?-1576.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>Newly imprinted.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Richard Schilders,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Middelburg :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1590?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>The fifth letter is reprinted from STC 13774.</note>
                  <note>Usually found as part 4 of "Master Derings workes" (see STC 6676).</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 6683 on UMI microfilm reel 1304, and as pt.3 of STC 6676b on reel 1685.</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of the originals in Cambridge University Library and the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
                  <note>Appears at reel 1304 (Cambridge University Library copy) and at reel 1685 (University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library copy).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:178438:1"/>
            <p>CERTAINE GODLY AND VERIE comfortable Letters, full of chriſtian conſolation. <hi>Written by M. Ed Dering vnto ſondry of his friends.</hi> And nowe publiſhed, for the proffite of the <hi>Church of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>2. THES. 1.15.</bibl> Stande faſt, &amp; keepe the inſtructions which ye haue bine taught, either by worde, or by our Epiſtles</q>
            <p>NEWLY IMPRINTED.</p>
            <figure>
               <q>NON VI SED VIRTUTE</q>
               <figDesc>decorative border incorporating the monogram of printer (RM)</figDesc>
            </figure>
         </div>
         <div type="last_words">
            <pb facs="tcp:178438:2"/>
            <head>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Derings wordes ſpoken on his death-bed at Tokye. The <hi>26.</hi> of Iune, <hi>1576.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>GOd forgeue me my negligence, that I haue not vſed the pretious giftes of God laid vp within me, more to his glory in my time: Yet I thanke God that I haue not vſed them in vaine glorie, or to pleaſe the vaine affections of men.</p>
            <p>After my death my enimies will become my friendes, except ſome that knowe me not, and thoſe which haue no feelinge of the trueth: For I haue faithfully ſerued the Lorde and my Prince in a good conſcience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>A Preacher ſaying vnto him: It is for thee a great bleſſing that thou ſhal depart in peace, and goe from many troubles that our brethren ſhall beare and ſee. He anſwered:</hi> I ſhall goe from many troubles and leaue many behinde me. If the Lord hath appointed that his ſaintes ſhall ſuppe togither, why goe I not to them: but if there bee any doubting or ſtaggering, our Lord reueale the trueth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hearing one ſay, He hoped that in his ſilence, his minde was neuertheles exerciſed in godly meditation. He anſwered:</hi> As a poore frayle man, and the leaſt of all the elect ſaints, yet beleeuing and lookinge on Chriſt my ſaluation. We ſhall all meete togither with the ſweet harmony of the Lord of hoſtes. What a cloude of wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes is heere: yet a little while and we ſhall ſee our hope. We haue ouertaken the endes of the worlde which is come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon vs, and we ſhall quicklie receyue the ende of our hope which we have waited for. Afflictions, ſicknes and payne, are but the worlds portions from the Lord. It is not to begin for a moment, but to continewe in the feare of God all our dayes: for in the twinckling of an eye we ſhalbe taken away. Dallie not with the worde of God, make not light of it: Bleſſed are they that vſe their tongues well when they haue it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>E. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letters">
            <pb facs="tcp:178438:2"/>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>An Epiſtle of M. Ed. Deringe, before his 24 Lecture on the Hebrues, which he preached the 6. of December, 1572. And gaue for a newe yeres gifte to the godlie in London &amp; elſewhere.</head>
               <head type="sub">To his verie louing friend Maiſter M. F.</head>
               <p>THe outward afflictions and manyfold troubles of a great nomber of gods childrie, whoſe trauel &amp; labour, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day to day J had ſtil in experience, and the inward feelling of many wou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded ſpirits, whoſe wofull ſighes and bitter mournings, J beheld in other, and had tried in my ſelfe: it made me very deſirous to ſeeke for remedies, to ſtoppe the complaints of ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous cryings, and to prepare our heartes in a ſtrong de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, that the fierie dartes of the Diuell might not wound vs. <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon this occaſion when J had to expound that place of the Apostle full of notable comfort: <hi>That Chriſte in the dayes of his fleſhe, offered vp prayers and ſupplications to him that was able to ſaue him from death, with ſtrong cryings and teares, and was deliuered from the thinges hee feared.</hi> J taried the longer in that matter, &amp; declared more at large what boldnes and aſſurance of hope was offered heere vnto all that ſhould obey the worde. Which whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I had done, as God gaue me vtterance, the poore in ſpirit, to whom J applyed my ſelfe, one or two required mee to ſette it downe in writinge, that it might be profitable to manie, which was comfortable to them. I durſt not reiect ſuch a good requeſt, but though ſometime I deferred it, yee I neuer forgot it, till I had written all as I was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
<pb facs="tcp:178438:3"/> Which when J had done, I purpoſed then with my ſelfe, to make it yet more common, and ſet it abroad in print: knowing aſſuredly, where God would giue it increaſe it ſhould bring forth the fruite of conſolation, that we might ſtande vpright in the day of euill. Thus hauing performed both the request of others, &amp; myne owne deſire, and the time fallinge out with the beginning of a newe yeare, I thought it not amiſſe to offer my labour to you, who I knowe would well accept of it as a newe yeares gift, though of no great price, yet of great good will: and though eaſilie obteyned, yet not little to bee esteemed. Therefore my deare brother, whom J loue in Christ, and reuerence in the worlde as many wayes J haue cauſe, ſo I offer it vnto you: The Lorde for his mercies ſake worke his owne good pleaſure, that J may haue of you the fruite that J de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, and you the grace that ye ſtande in neede of: that as God hath greatly bleſſed you, and made you abound in many graces to the glorie of his name, the comforte of your friends, and the benefite of his people: ſo your ioye, that it might be made perfect, you might alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounde in this, to haue a ſtrong faith against the daye of triall: which God of his mercie will ſurelie graunte vnto you, and finiſhe the good worke that hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gunne. Though J loue not to ſpeake faire (for flatterie and deceytful prayſes, I ſee what miſchief they breed) yet J feare not to beare you witnes of your well doing: the ſpirit of God hath planted humilitie more deepe in your breast, then that pride and arrogancie can pull it out. And in deede the better you are, the more effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all you doe ſee your owne vnworthineſſe, that all your righteouſnes is as a defiled clothe: and the more you
<pb facs="tcp:178438:3"/> approche vnto God, the more you abhorre your ſelfe, &amp; knowe that in our fleſhe there dwelleth no goodneſſe. Abraham our father; Job, Eſaie, and many other men of excellent vertue in the ſight of God, they haue beene all astoniſhed, to ſee howe their righteouſnes hath bene ſcattered away as the cloudes of the heauens. Paule cryeth out: O wretched man that I am, who ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer me from this body of death! But becauſe wee haue an enimie, that ſpareth not to diſplaye all our cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions before our eyes, to the ende he might make vs dispaire, therefore we may be bold, to the ſtrengthning of our hope, to ſet before vs againe, the ſpirituall graces that worke within vs, to aſſure our ſelues that we bee borne of God. So our Sauiour Christ prayſed manie that beleeued on him, ſo did the Apostles, ſo may we: and our heauenly Father will ratifie and confirme our wordes, when we ſpeake the trueth, accordinge to the meaſure of faith that euery one hath receyued. So Saint Iohn biddeth vs all be bolde, and not bee decey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued: He that doeth the things that are righteous, him ſelfe is righteous, and like vnto Christ in whom hee is ſanctified. So may J ſay vnto you, the grace of GOD hath wrought happily in you in theſe yeres &amp; conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of life, that ſo vnfainedly you haue ſought the Lorde. It can not be of your ſelfe, who are not able ſo much as to thinke a good thought, but it is of him, whoſe ſeede abideth in you. And although, becauſe you haue that treaſure in a brittle veſſell, you ſee ſometime the fruite of olde Adam, and the prickes of his tranſgreſſion within your bowelles: yet feare not his malice that hath wrought this woe: You are bought with a dearer price, then that ſinne may raigne againe within you, &amp;
<pb facs="tcp:178438:4"/> he that hath purchaſed you, hee will not ſuffer his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance to be ſpoyled. Jt is neceſſarie you ſhould know your ſinne, or you could not vnderstande howe great were your redemption. But your ſinnes can not ſepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate you away from him, who hath buried them in the earth, and will not ſee them any more. When you ſhall aſcende to come into his ſight, the earth will holde her owne, and keepe your ſinnes behinde you. The pear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing ſerpent ſhall not clime to accuſe you, nor the croo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked ſerpent ſhall not hyde your redemption from you. Your care is cast vpon him that careth for you, &amp; you knowe him who hath ſpoken: All power is giuen vnto me in heauen and in earth. Ye knowe him who hath a name aboue all names, that in the name of Jeſus all knees ſhall bowe: Euen hee that bought you with a price, and you are not your owne. If it bee poſſible for you to periſhe, then is it poſſible againe that Christe ſhould ſuffer iniurie. This boldnes you haue through him who hath made manifest his grace vnto you, that you denying impietie &amp; worldly concupiſcence, ſhould liue ſoberly, purely, and godly in this preſent life, and looke for the bleſſed hope that ſhall be reuealed, when all ſecretes ſhall be opened. To which iſſue and happy ende of life, the Lord bring both you and yours, in the fellowſhip of his ſaints, to prayſe his holy name, when he ſhall make knowen vnto you his glorie vnspeakea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and crowne it with immortalitie, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Farewell in Chriſt Ieſu, and pray for me.</salute>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>The 26. of December. 1572.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord to commaund,</hi> Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:178438:4"/>
               <head>A letter of M. Ed. Deringe to his brother Maiſter R. D.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt be with you euer Amen. For Maiſter S. whether he be angrie or no J knowe not, if he be God is witneſſe betweene him and me howe litle I haue deſerued it, true it is, hee ſeemed not very wel pleaſed, but if God be pleaſed mans good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wil, either it ſhalbe reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ciled, or ſhal not doe much hurt: if I haue the loſſe in worldlie thinges, I am content to beare it, and God will ſupply my want where I am able to doe nothing. J had leuer be your Brother not worth a grote, but hauing a good conſcience to praye for you, then haue (as I might) great liuing, &amp; encomber my co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience with much ſinne. And good Brother Dering, here followe me, you ſhalbe a great deale richer then you are: ſtudie the ſcripture, reade bookes, bee able to reaſon in your faith, especiallie and aboue all, haue a liuely feeling of God, that you thinke more vile of all the glorie of the world, then of the dust of the earth: you knowe we must all periſhe, and you must walke the way of all fleſhe: Our good Parents both Father &amp; Mother, they are gone before: you doe but waite the time, and you must goe after, your goods and landes must abide behinde, and the riches of your minde, they are onely your owne. You are my eldest brother, &amp; you knowe not howe glad I would be, to ſee you goe before me in Religion: God hath giuen you, neither a light heade nor little vnderstanding, if you would applie your ſelfe vnto knowledge, you ſhould then reape the fruit of your labour in more gladnes of heart then yet you can imagine: begin once but a little, and taste how ſweet the Lord is, and you ſhall feele the riches of his glorie, and ſay: Happie be the time that euer I knewe
<pb facs="tcp:178438:5"/> it. Let not good Brother, let not the worlde deceiue you, it is faithleſſe and deceiptfull, when you ſhall loue it best, it will ſoonest deceyue you. And of me thinke thus: that in the world I can not doe you ſo great a pleaſure, as continually to prouoke you to know God: and this I ſhalbe able to performe, though otherwiſe I ſhalbe able to pleaſure you nothing, and therefore I beſeeche you praye for me, and I will pray for you, &amp; ſo the Lord God ſhall helpe vs both, that I may be faith<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>full which way J am called, and you may bee ſuch as I deſire. And for Maister S. or any other of ſuch high calling, I loue them in the Lorde, euen as I loue myne owne ſoule, and will pray for them while they and I ſhall liue: Though I beare the loſſe of worldly things, yet by the grace of Christ, J will neuer loſe a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience: and though they be angrie with me, yet I will not leaue to pray for them, and commit my cauſe vnto God, he will one day multiplie his graces, where hee hath ſo well begun, and they ſhall (I trust) be through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie taught, whom God hath alreadie ſo farre instru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted. For my L. of C. J haue bene once with him, but J meane not yet to goe the ſeconde time, God will worke his will, his name be prayſed for euer. My L. of L. is a good man, I am often with him, I haue ſene in him ſo good tokens of a good ſpirit, that I reuerence him in my heart &amp; will ſerue him in Chriſt all wayes that J may. And for my doeing with any man, I praie you tell me wher you ſee me faultie, but if you know not of any ſin, doe not diſwade me from going vpright in the Gospell: But for my comfort, if you ſee me greeued, let me ſee in you, how you profeſſe the goſpell: &amp; perſwade your ſelf of this, that a liuely zeale, &amp; holy knowledg in you, and in my Siſter, ſhal make me gladder then any biſhoprike
<pb facs="tcp:178438:5"/> in England. The Lorde God for his mercies ſake that hath called you out of the kingdome of darkeneſſe, and placed you in the fellowſhippe of his ſaintes in light, make you to feele the depth of his graces, that you may be renewed, confirmed, ſtrengthened, and made per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fite vnto the ende, Amen. Fare you well in Christ Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſu, and doe my hartie commendations to my ſister.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From London, <date>the xix. of Nouember.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your louing brother</hi> Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To his brother Maiſter R. D.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lord Jeſu Christ bee with you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen. Good brother, I would gladlie write oftener vnto you, but otherwiſe I haue ſo much to doe, that ſome time I forget many dueties. Another cauſe is, J haue nothing to write as I would, ſo I haue no pleaſure to doe that I would not. So it is, that I am for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to preach: which grieueth me most, then ſlaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derous reportes doe hurt me much, where J would fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest pleaſe, ſo farre as I may in the feare of God. But how ſo euer things are, it is a bleſſed ſentence whiche he hath ſpoken, who will ſurelie performe it: To them that loue God, all things happen to the best, and pray for me good Brother, that I may holde ſtedfast that loue, and wauer not in the faith of the gospell in which we haue aſſured life: and as I am bounde J trust I will pray for you, that your eyes may haue perfect &amp; pure ſight, to ſee the louing countenance of the Lorde which is better then life: ſo you ſhall bee happie euen in the dayes of your vanitie, and when nature ſhall make you yeelde to the neceſſitie of all fleſhe, to goe walke in the way of all the worlde, then ſhall you reape the fruite of your labour, and ſay with gladnes: <hi>Lord nowe letteſt thou thy ſeruaunt depart in peace.</hi> This is all the
<pb facs="tcp:178438:6"/> hope we haue, and the onely ioye that is to be looked for vnder the heauens: the nearer you ſhall feele it, the more you ſhall ſee it, it ſhall delight you and ſet you on a ſure ground, that you ſhall not be aſhamed for euer. The Lord God for his Christes ſake ſtrengthen vs all to ſo good a purpoſe, and the mutuall debte we owe one to another in the bound of nature, let vs paye it in this holy affection, to praye for our perſeuerance vnto the ende. And as touching the iſſue of all my buſineſſe, looke for the worst, hope for the best, and beare what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer ſhall fall. J trust to God once I ſhall ſee the day wherein J ſhall faithfully ſpeake it, euen as Saint Paul <hi>Vita mea no<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt chara mihi, vt conſuma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> curſum meu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> gaudio</hi> The Bb. and many other ſeeke occaſions against mee. God hath ſtil rayſed me vp many friendes, but my hope is onely in him, that hath kept me hitherto, and not in man, when J knowe what ende will come, you ſhall heare: If I would loſe the trueth I could winne the world, but that were a miſerable change. God bleſſe vs and ſende vs peace, make vs wiſe in his Gospell, and ſtedfast vnto the ende. My Wife hath bene I thanke God in no trouble, neyther was any toward her, that J knowe of, if any fall, God hath made her rich in grace and knowledge to giue accompt of her doing. D.W. on frydaie last as I was about to preach, forbad me in hir Maieſties name, ſo I ſtande now forbidden, not by the Bb. but by our Princeſſe, whom J beſeech God make a happie gouernour in his church, and many yeares to giue peace vnto his people. If we prayed as we ſhould, God would make perfite the good worke hee hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun, and make vs ſee the peace of Jeruſalem all the dayes of our life. And J beſeeche God, that wee may wiſhe ſo effectually his mercies, that at last hee may
<pb facs="tcp:178438:6"/> ſhutt vs vp in a bleſſed vnitie, that they whom he hath afflicted, may reioyce. Commende me to all. Thank<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> my coſen, for her letters, and for the parſonage ſhe wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth of: I will not refuſe it if I may haue it, neyther will I ſue for it though it were much better. If God call me to it, I pray God I may doe my duetie: if not, yet his will be done. I am perſwaded, if I be ſetled there, it ſhalbe a bleſſinge vnto the countrie: if not, without me God keepeth thoſe that bee his. Farewell good Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, And the Lord keepe you and all yours, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The 24. of December 1573.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>Your louing Brother, Edwarde Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To his Brother I. D.</head>
               <p>THE God of all grace who giueth vs eyes to ſee, and eares to heare, giue vnto vs euer his holy ſpirit, that in the middeſt of a darke world, we may ſee the bright<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his heauenly kingdome, and in this weake ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle of ſmall co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuance, we may knowe the dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling place which we ſhall haue for euer in the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the iust, Amen. I thanke you, good brother, for your letter, and for your care of my recouerie, but most of all becauſe you ſhewe a good teſtimonie of your minde, that the feare of God doeth dwell in you: of this J am gladde, and I am ſure I ſhalbe glad. For I know howe earnestlie I deſire it, and I ſee howe vnfainedlie you are brought vnto it, and when the Lord in his good will, &amp; his appointed time ſhal make vs ſee more cleare howe great this bleſſinge is, we knowe wee ſhall reape the fruite of it in the ſight of his preſence and in eternal life, this is enough for vs: a ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth vnto our hope, a ſtay vnto our faith, a continuance vnto our loue, lett the
<pb facs="tcp:178438:7"/> good worke of God be finiſhed in vs. And of this wee may be ſure, whoſoeuer regardeth it not, or elſe embra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth the preſent worlde, he knoweth not God, nor yet hath euer ſeene the length &amp; breadth of immortalitie. And therefore good brother, (becauſe bleſſed are the eyes which ſee that we ſee,) let vs ſtrenghten our ſight, with the ſweet oyntement of Gods ſpirite, that we may yet ſee more cleare, till through all the graces of GOD our Father, we may ſee our bodies alſo raiſed vp from the dead, and our ſelues ioyned vnto our Sauior Chriſt by decree and ſentence which neuer ſhalbe reuerſed, Come you bleſſed vnto eternall life: vnto this, a good conſcience will carie vs with ioye &amp; gladnes. Beyonde this our ſenſes faile vs, and our hearte is able to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehende nothing of the glorie which we ſhall ſee. Only J knowe it is exceeding great, whoſe greatneſſe I can neither ſee, nor heare, nor comprehende with thought: And therefore if euer thinge delighted vs, or if euer we haue ſeene pleaſure, or can wiſhe the thing in which we would reioyce, let vs turne all our affections hither with harte and ſoule, life and ſtrength, to delight in this, which alone is all, and no body ſhall take it from vs. And ſure brother, this is true, if God haue recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vs to that bleſſed kingdome, he hath appointed the time in which he will giue vs his ſpirite (though not fullie) to comprehende it, yet ſo farre to ſee it, that wee will accounte all the worlde to be but dunge, to the ende we may winne Christ. And this J am perſwaded, good brother, God hath and will giue plentifullie vnto you, ſo that you ſhall vſe the worlde as though you vſed it not, and be here with men, as one whoſe dwelling were with the Angels of God, vſing your calling in any godly
<pb facs="tcp:178438:7"/> recreatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but hauing your heart nearest vnto God, that gaue it: and the Lorde graunt you this happines, that all the pleaſure of your life maye bee in deede accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, ſuch as ſhall not after be mingled with ſhame &amp; ſorrowe. And J beſeeche God bleſſe my good <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncle B. and make him now to know, which in his tender yeres he could not ſee: for the worlde was then darke, and we were blinde in it: but ſince we haue bene lightened with the gospell of the Lorde Jeſus, and ſo much more earnest lie nowe we must pray that it may be vnto vs the gospell of healthe, and wee may increaſe in the knowledge of the mysterie of it. And the Lorde open his gracious countenance reuealed in it, vnto my Aunte, that ſhee may alſo make a bleſſed chaunge, to leaue vaine imaginations of her own minde, which are full of ignorance, and learne the ſcripture, which can make knowen vnto her the liuinge God. And com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende me hartilie vnto them both, to whom <hi>I</hi> wiſhe as to my ſelfe.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Your louing Brother, Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A comfortable Letter written by Maiſter Ed. Deringe, to a Chriſtian Gentlewoman, <hi>in heauines of ſpirite.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>JT is true (good Maistres H.) which the ſpirit hath ſpoken, and we feele it by experience, <hi>That by many tribulations we muſt enter into the kingdome of heauen.</hi> This is a common decree which God hath ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctified to be a lot for all his children. So the authour and finiſher of our faith, Jeſus Christ him ſelfe was made perfect. Into his ſimilitude we are alſo predesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate
<pb facs="tcp:178438:8"/> that we ſhould first die with him, and then be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>takers of his glorie: Lett vs not therefore refuſe that condition of life in which we haue the fellowſhipp of all the Saintes of God, but rather confeſſe with the holy Apostle, That <hi>bleſſed is the man who endureth temptation.</hi> But becauſe all afflictions are bitter for the preſent time, and when the minde is ſhaken with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowe, it is then most eaſilie cast downe of the enemie, let vs learne wiſelie what our troubles are, and be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared of remedie in the day of triall. All our afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are eyther according to the fleſhe, in hunger, colde, nakedneſſe, ſhame, contempt, ſlaunder, &amp;c. or accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Spirite, in lamentations and mourninges, which the worlde knoweth not. The firste euilles are eaſilie borne, for they are all but vanitie, and in vanitie they ſhall dye: if we ſee no fauour in the ſight of the Sunne that ſhineth not here acceptable vnto vs, when we haue payde the debt we owe vnto death, the Lorde will deliuer vs from all the iniuries of men. But in this behalfe let me co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort my ſelfe, God hath ſet you free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch afflictions. Your goodes are vnto you in a liberall portion, your life made happie with a louing huſbande, your calling acceptable vnder a gracious and good Mistreſſe, in whoſe ſight you haue founde fauour, in this estate you feele no trouble, therefore I let it paſſe. The other affliction which is of the spirite, and whiche can not be reſisted with any earthlie bleſſing, looke for it aſſuredlie, for it will come vnto you, that you maye ſuffer with Christ, and reigne with him in glorie. Theſe troubles they come many wayes, euen as the spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite of God doeth leade vs vnto life. First we are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to learne &amp; knowe the worde of God, against
<pb facs="tcp:178438:8"/> this looke for many tentations, the enimie will trie whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che way to plucke that out of our heartes: Out of the worde we must learne a precious faith, and holde that vnmoueable before God: againſt this what temptations are betweene heauen and earth, you ſhal feeele your por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, if any thing poſſible ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> diſcourage you. With faith you must ioyne a liuelie hope, which is, a longinge ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion of Gods glorie: in this alſo Sathan will pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termitte nothing to quenche your affections, that it may be dead, and to darken your minde that you may ſee nothing, without theſe you can not poſſiblie liue, and vnto theſe you can not poſſiblie come, but first you ſhall feele what is the ſtrength of ſinne. And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding faint not, the Lion hath ouercome which is of the tribe of Iuda. The force of the Serpent ſhall bruſe our heele, but it ſhall not take away from vs the head-piece of ſaluation. Learne therefore first the worde of God, this is the ſeede of regeneration, by which wee are made newe creatures, this is the bread of ſpiritual nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment, by which we are growne vp into eternall life. This is the weapon of our warfare, by whiche wee may wounde and driue away our enimies. This is the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of our glorious kingdome, by which wee doe knowe that God doeth reigne in vs. Take this vnto you, the ſhielde of your defence, the ſtrength of your age, the wiſedome of your heart, and the ſafetie of your life, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended vnto you in the worde of Christ. Searche the Scriptures, and ſeale it in your heart with a good per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion that it is the word of God and of life, and hee hath grauen in it an expreſſe image of eternall trueth. Let it dwell plentifullie within you, and your heart is armed with a most ſtrong defence, all enimies ſhall fall
<pb facs="tcp:178438:9"/> before it, the wiſedome of the wiſe ſhalbe brought to nought, and the councell of the prudent ſhalbe made fooliſh, the wayes of the aduerſaries ſhalbe ſcattered, and the ſcorners ſeate ſhall bee throwen downe, ſo true it is that the Lorde hath ſpoken. Bleſſed is the man whoſe delight is in the Lawe of the Lorde, and whoſe meditation is in it day and night. Lett vs then bringe downe the hautineſſe of our mindes, and receyue with meekeneſſe the worde grafted in vs, which can ſaue our ſoules. To this deſire of vnderstanding, when God hath brought vs, then let vs pray to be deliuered from temptatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and take heede we be not ſpoyled of ſo great a treaſure. We haue three especiall enimies in this be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe, of which S. Paule biddeth vs all beware: the one is, <hi>Phyloſophie,</hi> that is, a vayne and curious ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching of Gods mysteries, or meaſuring things reuealed according to our vnderstandinge, with which tentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons whylest our Fathers were ouercome, they became fooliſhe in their owne imaginations, and chaunged the glorie of God into the likeneſſe of a corruptible man, making Images, praying to Angelles, imageninge of ſoules like little children, deuiſing Purgatorie, reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of Gods wiſedome aboue our capacitie: As if we be predestinate we may liue as we list, if wee are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to worke, if our dayes are nombred, why ſeeke we any ſafetie to our life. Jf the Angelles doe keepe vs in all our wayes, that we ſhal not hurt our foote againſt a ſtone, why feare wee any falling? Theſe phantaſies, and worſe then theſe, diſquiet our mindes and fight within vs against our humble obedience to the worde of God. Which all when we haue ouercome (and ſaide with the Prophete: ſecrete things are for the Lorde, but
<pb facs="tcp:178438:9"/> things reuealed for vs and our children) yet haue wee no peace. A ſeconde enimie riſeth vp greater then the first, which Saint Paule calleth <hi>The traditions of men,</hi> for the heart of man which drinketh in errour, as the grounde doeth drinke water, is very obstinatlie bounde with olde customes and longe continuance, meaſuring trueth which is pure and holy, only by time which is corrupt and euill, and not onely this, but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo hath inflamed our affections to loue to much our fathers wayes, to like their opinions, to esteeme their iudgementes, to prayſe their doeinges, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mende their age, to talke of their names, till throughe manie entiſements we are at last bewitched, our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is ſtolen away, and trueth is taken from vs: by this meanes all corruptions which haue ouerflowed the earth, haue ſtill wyde roomes in the heartes of manie. The Popes ſupremacie, Latin ſeruice, prayer for the dead, Maſſes, Diriges, Pardons, Pilgrimages, Sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſinge, and all poperie, with the authours of it, Popes, Cardinalls, Monkes, Fryers, all which haue neither trueth, nor ſhadowe of trueth: not one worde of them is in all the Goſpell of Christ, onely olde cuſtome hath bredde it in our bones, and an opinion of our fathers hath printed it in our brestes, and wee will not cast it out. But the Lorde be thanked, who hath had mercie vpon vs, to make vs holde faste the worde of trueth, what ſoeuer our fathers haue vainely taught vs, and yet we are not in ſecuritie. But a thirde enimie is in the harte of man, that the worde of God may not haue his perfect honour, and that is an opinion conceyued of earthlie thinges, and planting of holynes in corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible creatures, as in Meates, Drinkes, Dayes, Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes,
<pb facs="tcp:178438:10"/> conditions of life, places, tymes, Ceremonies, neyther hearing our Sauiour Christ, that God is a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, and onely hee is to bee worſhipped in Spirite and Trueth. Neither his Apostle Paule, That the Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of that worlde commende vs not vnto God, for neyther if we eate, are we euer the worſe: neither if we eate not, are we euer the better. Theſe and many great temptations ſtand againſt vs aſſoone as we would giue ouer our ſelues to the worde of God, whiche is the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of a christian life. Trowe you that in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance of our courſe and journey, before we come at our Sauiour Christ, ſhall we not be ſifted and tryed to ſee what is within vs? And you (good Maistres H.) to applie this to your ſelfe, tell mee howe you haue lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Christ, hath his Goſpell bene peaceable in you from the first day till nowe, without all contradiction? Was your mynde neuer puffed vp in vayne imaginations? Did the traditions &amp; perſwaſions of men neuer ſhake your thoughte? Haue you not bene tempted with opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions of creatures, as though ſome were more holy, ſome more prophane? J knowe as you long after Christ and deſire his trueth in ſingle heart: ſo his grace you haue not, without ſharpe and bitter tryalls, and the more freely the worde of God ſhall poſſeſſe your ſoule, and fill your heart with all deſire of it, the more you ſhall feele what fight is against it, looke for the like in all your life, and when you approche to the true feare of God, prepare your heart to the ſtrongest aſſault. The worde of God thus made knowen vnto vs, and when we followe it with all our ſoule, that wee may haue a liuely faith to reioyce at the promiſes of God, to feare at his threatninge, and feele a full perſwaſion of a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine
<pb facs="tcp:178438:10"/> performance of all his wordes: O Lorde, what is the malice of Sathan! And though many tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are against vs, the longe prosperitie of the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked in which they triumphe, why lest the goodneſſe of God prouoketh them ſtill to repentance, the bitter ſigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the godly, in which they mourne vnder manie croſſes, whyles God maketh their faith pretious before him: theſe haue rooted quite out of the heartes of the vngodly, the faith and trueth whiche they owe vnto God, ſo that against all his iudgementes, they haue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened their mouth, and ſaid aloude: <hi>Where is the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of his comming?</hi> And against all his mercies they haue proclaymed warre, and ſaide, <hi>They wil not haue Chriſt to reigne ouer them.</hi> But theſe tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions Christ hath ouercome in vs, and giuen vs his ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rite, in which we knowe aſſuredlie that the Lord reig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth: neyther ſlacketh he his comminge, as many ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counte ſlacknes, but he will come, and his glorie ſhalbe knowen. And yet we are not in peace, but Sathan will ſifte vs another way: he will laye our ſinnes before vs, to make vs feare, that tht promiſes of God belonge not vnto vs, and this of all temptations is the greatest, yet we feare not, for what belongeth to all our ſinnes, which Christ hath not borne? ſorrowe, ſicknes, death, hell, condemnation, were they not in his body, and are they not all crucified vpon the croſſe? Is he not riſen from them, &amp; hath he not broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the chaynes of death, and ſo is aſcended into glorie? If this bee my feare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I am a ſinner, rather let mee reioyce, for Christ hath taken my ſinnes vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him, &amp; hath buried the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per then the bottome of the Sea, he hath led it openly in triumphe, and nayled it vpon the croſſe fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> henceforth
<pb facs="tcp:178438:11"/> &amp; for euermore it hath no ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth, whoſoeuer ſeeme to colour it as redd as ſcarlet, or make it like purple, it is ſtill nothing, and casteth but a vayne terrour before our eyes: we will neuer denie this but freelie confeſſe it, that we be miſerable ſinners, and not worthie to lifte vp our eyes to heauen, but who will lay our ſinnes to our charge, nowe God hath iustified vs? or what ſinne can rest vpon vs, now Christ hath waſhed them awaye? That which once was in fight with Christ, and he hath ouercome it, who ſhall ſet too his hande the ſeconde time, to make the victorie perfect? This is true, and euerlasting trueth hath ſealed it vp, that ſinne is aboliſhed for euer and euer, howſoeuer wee feare or tremble, or bee faint harted, yet before the Lorde with whom our life is hidde, there is no perill, no daunger, no feare, but peace &amp; righteouſnes with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ende. Let our ſinnes be neuer ſo great, neither wee nor our ſinnes can chaunge the newe Testament, that God is mercifull to our ſinnes, and will blot out all our tranſgreſſions: therefore this care is past, that our ſinnes be many, the more they are, the greater is his mercy, who hath forgiuen them. And this is the to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken which God hath giuen vs, that we are his, becauſe we are grieued with our ſinnes, for our Sauior Christ ouercame ſinne with paynes and ſufferinges which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long vnto it, and this is the badge of our redemption, to be made like him in afflictions, wee haue ſinne, and abhorre it, it woundeth vs with feare, it ſetteth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs condemnation, we haue a ſence and feeling of Gods anger against it, and hell gnaweth vppon our ſoules becauſe of tranſgreſſion. O bleſſed ſtate, and treaſure of gladnes, this was the Jmage of Christe
<pb facs="tcp:178438:11"/> when he ouercame ſinne, a marke of my redemption in myne owne fleſhe, that I ſhould not fainte. As the ſunne maketh the day, and the night darkenes, ſo this affliction of ſinne is the badge and cogniſance of our certaine forgiuenes. And herein ſee the goodnes of God, which turneth all things to the best to thoſe that loue him. Through feare of ſinne the Diuell fighteth againſt vs, without feare of ſinne we could neuer haue boldnes: through anguiſhe of heart the Diuell would ouerwhelme vs with ſorrowe: without anguiſh of hart we could neuer haue ioye. In feelinge Gods anger, the Diuell would make vs to dispaire: without feelinge his threatning, and trembling before him, we could ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer haue ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gth of faith, that his mercies are for euer. In all ſuffrings I am like to Christ, they are the marks of mine adoption, that J am his childe. Doe wee not heare the Lorde? Himſelfe doeth ſpeake, <hi>If wee bee without correction, then are we baſtardes and not ſonnes:</hi> and to ſhewe what our correction ſhalbee, hee ſayeth in an other place: <hi>If we bee planted with him into the ſimilitude of his death, then ſhall wee alſo be partakers of his reſurrection.</hi> Who hath heard ſo great ſaluation as this? Euery weapon wherewith the enemie ſtriketh, the ſame armeth vs to greater ſalua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: And euery wounde that we doe receyue, the ſame confirmeth vs to a ſurer life. Then (as before I ſaide) care not for ſinne, for that is aboliſhed, ſo here I maye adde, care not for hell, for the nearer wee feele it, the further we are from it. Let them feare ſinne that feele it not, and let them be afraide of condemnation that knowe not what it is, vppon whom destruction ſhall come ſodenlie as an armed man. Our eyes haue bene
<pb facs="tcp:178438:12"/> kept waking, and we haue ſeene our ſinnes: our harts haue fainted before the anger of the Lorde, And wee haue not deſpiſed his heauenlie callinge, therfore in the day of trouble, we ſhall haue rest. In this perſwaſion we will liue and die: and if our ſoules ſhould melte for feare within vs, although the Lorde ſhould kill vs, yet would we trust in him. Abraham beleeued in the Lorde, and it was imputed vnto him for righteouſnes, against hope hee beleeued vnder hope: and if our hope ſeemed to be taken from vs, yet would wee patientlie wayte the Lords leaſure, vntill hee ſaue our hope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne, that at the leaſt our faith might haue againe the glorie and trueth of full aſſurance. Another thing we must labour in, and in another thinge wee ſhall haue temptation, and that is, that wee may ſee what is the glorie of God and immortall life: herein lett vs medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate in our beddes, and thinke on this in our ſecret pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in the middeſt of our companies, let theſe cogitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons be often in our hartes, and in all places let theſe be our muſes. When we ſhal apprehende with all the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of God what is the height, the bredth, the length, the depth, wee ſhall knowe that the glorie is great of immortalitie, and he is onely to bee beleued, who ſhall ſhine in honour when this vanitie is ouerpaſt His ſtrength is great that layde the foundations of the world, and his brightnes exceeding, that made the Sunne and the Moone. His treaſure and ritches, are aboue meaſure, who hath giuen Princes their golde and ſiluer and other pretious ſtones for the honour of man: he in deede is of excellent maiestie, who is King of Kings, and Lord of Lordes, and his power is aboue all, who maketh ſickneſſe his meſſengers, and death
<pb facs="tcp:178438:12"/> his minister, till he ſhall aboliſhe them both. For his mercies are vnspeakable, that forgiueth vs all our ſinnes, and his goodnes is great, who hath had regarde to the children of men. From nothing hee brought vs into life, he kept vs from the graue, he will restore vs, and make vs ſee his glorie. When I would thinke on this, my ſoule is compaſſed with dulnes of fleſhe, that J cannot ſee the fulnes of his fauour: When I would conſider in my heart what is his grace: Darkeneſſe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſhadoweth myne vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding, &amp; all my thoughts doe vaniſhe in his immortalitie. When J would ſpeake of his louing kindnes, my tonge cleaueth to the roote of my mouthe, and my wordes ſticke faste within my lippes. But this one thinge in all myne infirmities J can perceyue, that his glorie is exceeding great, whoſe glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie I can not comprehende, and the life is longe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed vnto man, where his heart and minde can ſee no ende. If all the worlde were a flowing water, and euery yeare one droppe ſhould be diminiſhed, the Sea ſhould be all made drye, and the bottomes of the deepe ſhould appeare, before he ſhall ceaſe to lyue, whom God hath rayſed from the dead, and this breadth &amp; wide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe betweene heauen and earth, if it ſhould bee filled vp, and euery yeare but one handfull of earth added to the worke: yet ſooner ſhould the great distance bee clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp, and the emptie places made full, then hee ſhall ceaſe from ioye and gladnes, who ſhall ſtande in the reſurrection of the iust. This is the glorie that hath neither ſpot nor blemiſhe, before which me thinketh, not only Princes and the glorie of the world, but the Sunn and Moone &amp; all the hostes of heauen are nothing els but meere vanitie, for death ſhadoweth the glorie of
<pb facs="tcp:178438:13"/> man, though hee ſpred his braunches neuer ſo farre, yet the graue cloſſeth vp in little roome the ambitious heart, which before was enlarged from East to West. And the Heauens that are high and free from death, yet are holden vnder the tyrannie of enuious and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuming tyme, in which they ſhalbe chaunged: Only the Lord is in honor and maiestie, who hath ſet eternitie rounde about him, and cast out tyme vnto confuſion. Oh Lorde, where are their eyes that ſee not this, or their hearts that ſee and regarde it not! Who hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>witched them, in the countenances of men, to carrie the heartes of beastes, and to forget the latter ende. The Lorde turne them that runne astray, that they may knowe and ſee where is their glorie, but the tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions haue ouertaken them. Which are against our honour when the Lorde ſhall deliuer them from euill, they ſhall giue thankes and reioyce with vs, that they alſo haue eyes to ſee. And bleſſed are you (good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtres H.) and God hath viſited you in an acceptable time, whoſe heart he hath touched with feare, &amp; whoſe afflictions he hath filled with hunger and thirst, that you ſhould mourne for the redemption that is in Chriſt, and be pleaſed with nothing but with the grace of his countenance. This is a Schoolemistres to bringe you vnto him, and a bond to tye you faste, that you ſhall not be ſeperated: and accompliſhe J beſeeche you, this good worke of his grace, till you loue the Lord withall your heart, and till you can ſay with the bleſſed Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>I deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>For this purpoſe wee are chastiſed of the Lorde, and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our faith is tryed, at the laſt it ſhalbe made ſtrong, that with it we may quench all the fierie dartes of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than,
<pb facs="tcp:178438:13"/> and in righteouſnes and peace, and ioye of the holy Ghoste, runne the courſe that is ſet before vs, till in a bleſſed iſſue of happie dayes, with a good ſpirite we may ſay boldlie, <hi>Lorde, nowe letteſt thou thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt depart in peace.</hi> Which I beſeeche God the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Jeſus Christ, the God of mercie, and Father of all conſolation graunt vnto you, Amen.</p>
               <p>Pray, pray, pray, praye, this is your beſt ſeruice whereſoeuer your duetie is moſt bounde.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters of Ed. Der. to Maiſtres B.</head>
               <p>GRace, mercie and peace from God our Father, &amp;c. J had much leuer good Maistres B. come my ſelf then write vnto you, but as other things are farre con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to my deſire, ſo is it in my comming vnto you, &amp; J am constrayned rather to write then to come, but God appointes our wayes, whether J come and be with you, or elſe be other where and heare from you, J trust and am perſwaded, that both I ſhall heare from you, and you ſhall haue the ſame constancie in the loue of trueth and ſtill increaſe in the knowledge of it, till the good grace of God haue made the worke perfect that it hath begunne, and you with all your harte and all your ſoule doe feare the Lorde, and delight in all obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of his holy will. Wherevnto though we be ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficientlie perſwaded by the nature of godlines it ſelfe, which all men doe prayſe, and the righteous doe loue: yet a greater prouocation is in you, becauſe God hath giuen you a good estate, in whiche your example ſhall doe good to many, and becauſe good hath filled you with a hartie affection to testifie his Religion, that you
<pb facs="tcp:178438:14"/> may accordingly in all weldoing ſurmount the praiſe of your profeſſion, and eſpecially becauſe he that hath called you is holy, that you may expreſſe his ſimilitude and likenes in all your wayes, and this good courſe through euill dayes, when God of his mercy ſhall make ſtreight vnto vs wee ſhall ſee then what is the latter end. Our hartes ſhalbe ſatiſfied with it, and our tonge ſhal ſpeake not as the world doth, bleſſed are the riche me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> or bleſſed are the mighty, for all theſe haue winges to flie away, and highe eſtates to ſit downe in the duſt, when man must goe make his bed in the darke, and ſay to coruption thou art my father, and to the worme thou art my mother and ſiſter, but our ſonge ſhalbe in better hermonie, and wee ſhall ſay with the Prophet Dauid, bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lorde and delights greatly in his commaundeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts: For when all hatred ſhall growe againſt this, and all aduerſity ſhall ſtryue to come vppon it, yet all is nothing and ſhall not moue it. For when our hart is ſtrenghtened with this grace, wee ſee our portions in all eſtates and tymes: in diſcredit, we ſee praiſe, in pouerty, riches, in anger, fauour, in darknes, light, in bondage, libertie, and in death, life, yea whatſoeuer in weaknes of bodie, in en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uie of tyme, in vncertainty of eſtate, in danger of life, or in any thinge els, becauſe nothinge can ſeperat vs from the loue of God, nothinge can turne vnto our harme, for wee haue his promiſe that is able to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme it, that to thoſe that loue God all things happen for the beſt. This purpoſe of life is ſoone had, and this courſe is eaſly begon, but the frute of it doth not vade nor the gladnes of it ſhall neuer bee loſte ſo that wee ſhall not, nor by the grace of God we: will not for ſo
<pb facs="tcp:178438:14"/> litle labour loſe ſo great a reward, nor for a litle pleaſure which vainlie wee thinke is in other thinges, receaue the reward of our fooliſhnes, which aſſuredlie wee knowe hath euerlaſtinge griefe, wee haue not ſo vnfruictfullie learned Chriſt nor ſo vnhappelie geuen witneſſe of his trueth, But better thinges belonge vnto vs, in better wayes wee wll run our courſe, in a better hope lay downe our bodies: The children of the worlde ſhall make the worlde their portion, wee looke for another citty of which the Lord is the workeman, and wee will not buylde vp our vnhappines in the vayne deſires and concupiſcence of this world, neither yet (ſeinge God is good to vs to fill our dayes with peace) will wee deny any comfort that is offered vs in this preſent pilgrimage, but ſeeinge the earth is the Lordes and all that therin is, wee haue perfect plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in frendes, riches, authoritie, honnor: if all bee his? All are pure: if all bee of him? Jn all is pleaſures for where his kingdome is, there is righteouſnes and peace and ioye of the holy Ghoſt: and ſorrowe and ſinne is caſt out, only let vs care as all thinges are good, ſo we vſe them: and as they are corrupt, ſo to let them alone. S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. Paule teacheth that to the pure all thinges are pure, but to the impure all thinges are impure: And the thinges of this worlde are made accordinge to the conſcience of man: Houlde this to remember it at noone dayes, and lett our reynes inſtruct vs in it in the night ſeaſon, that wee feell our hartes inflamed with the loue of God, and that it may bee acceptable vnto vs as our owne life, to ſett forth his praiſe: That wee acknowledge his glorie whiche ſhineth in all his
<pb facs="tcp:178438:15"/> his workes, and then the Lorde hath ſet vs in a large rome of libertie, where we walke with boldnes in good delight of his creatures: and in deed and in trueth this it is when this affliction hath taken roote within mee, and I feele the worke of it perpetually within my minde, whether J be following my Hauke or my bowle, J make a more acceptable ſacrifice to God, then the harte barren of this loue of God can doe: though the knee bowe or the tongue ſay, prayſed be the Lorde, for euery one that ſayeth, Lorde, Lorde, ſhall not enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the kingdome of heauen, but in whom ſo euer the loue of God doeth reigne, and hath driuen out the lewde deſires of a diſſolute minde, him God hath cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen, and the ſpirit of his ſonne Christ cryeth within him, Our Father: yet I meane not here to iustifie theſe worldly minded men, to whom the day is to ſhort for their vaine playes, except they reach it out till mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>night at Cardes and Dice: ſuch people as they, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly fill all their delightes with blaſphemie, ſo lett them knowe that the loue of the liuing God they neuer felt, but the god of this worlde hath blinded their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beleeuing heartes, and in their vncleannes there I leaue them, till the ſinnes of their youth bee rotten in their bones, that they may ſinke deepe in their owne ſhame. My meaning is, that the man of God whoſe ſoule doeth thirste to ſee his glorie, and hath the ioye of his life in immortalitie, in respect of the which hee accounteth all the worlde to be but dunge: I ſaye, that man may haue true delight in the dayes of his vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, the ſmelling of the dogge, the flying of the birde, the qualities of all creatures, they were made for him: and he is iniurious to the blood of Christ, that thinkes
<pb facs="tcp:178438:15"/> he may not vſe them: but all theſe things are good for our recreation, to comfort the frailtie of weake bodyes, and to bring refreſhing to a wearie ſpirite: which end, if we forget, and make it our paſtime, and ſo call it, then we turne our paſtime into ſinne. For what is our tyme that we are wearie of it, or what is our life that ſeemeth ſo ſlowe to paſſe, are we grieued with the light which the Lorde hath ſet in the Heauens, or is the feeling of our body burdenous vnto vs, or our eyelyd<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des payned with being open, or are our eares wounded with the ſounde of the ayre, or what griefe, what care, what ſorrowe is it, why we wiſhe our time forgotten &amp; past? Surely <hi>Iob</hi> knewe not this when hee ſaide, His time paſſed faſter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> a poſte: nor Dauid knewe it not whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he thought his life but a ſpanne longe: and ſurely he hath but a wretched lyfe, &amp; let him not loue it, who is fayne to runne to the birdes of the ayre, and the beaſtes of the fielde, to ſeeke ſome comfort againſt it. And therefore (good Maiſtres B.) let paſtime alone, and be not wearied with your good dayes, your tymes are paſſed meetely well, and you haue ſeene <hi>40.</hi> yeares filled and gone, the reſidue behinde will paſſe with them, You ſhall not holde them if you would, but pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtyme and they will dwell togither, till our appointed time ſhall come: and one ende ſhalbe vnto all. But then you ſhall ſee another ſtate, and this enimitie betweene vs and it, ſhalbe taken away: we ſhall not be wearie of it to wiſhe it gone, and it will not bee wearie of vs to weare vs away, but Tyme and we ſhall dwell togither, and the glorie of God ſhalbe eternally before vs, and we before his Maieſtie in Jmmortalitie. A bleſſed ſtate, a hope of lyfe, a glorious body, a heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly minde,
<pb facs="tcp:178438:16"/> and woe be to all theſe tyme paſſers of, that know how to delight in this, but haue more pleaſure in all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleannes: when the end of their labour ſhall come vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon them, they ſhall feele more griefe in one day, then after ſhalbe eaſed world without ende. And in one ſentence of an angrie Judge <hi>(goe you curſed into e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall fire)</hi> they ſhalbe wounded with that miſerie, whiche worlde without end ſhall rest vpon them, and their olde pastime ſhall neuer more be founde: but this is the portion of them that knowe not God. But you good Maistres B. haue alreadie paſſed the dayes of your ignorance, and the kingdome of heauen is come vnto you with power: you loue the trueth of the Lorde Jeſus, and all falſe wayes you doe abhorre: you doe feele the hope of the Elect of God, and it hath quen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched the deſires of vngodlie. Pray ſtill, that you may haue increaſe: and read the Scriptures, in whiche you ſhall haue comfort: theſe will leade you in a perfect way, and neyther Paule nor Peter haue a more bleſſed end, then is for vs, in a like pretious faith: and J (as J am bounde) will beſeeche the God of mercie, and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of our Lord Ieſus Christ, that he will looke vpon you, to fill you with his grace and holy ſpirite, that it may guyde you and all your children before you, and your houſhold committed to your charge, that you may dwell in the newe and bleſſed Testament of the forgiuenes of ſinnes through faith in Christ Ieſus, who hath destroyed the workes of the Diuell, and is able to keepe you for euer more. And to his gracious defence, J hartely leaue you and all yours.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord</hi> Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:178438:16"/>
               <head>To Maiſtres B.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lord Ieſus Christ be with you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen. Good Maistres <hi>Baret,</hi> howe fayne J would be with you, God knoweth, and howe I am in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debted to doe good in your houſe, if J ſhould not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe, I must needes accuſe my ſelfe of much vnthanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulnes, but God alone dispoſeth all our wayes, to be ſo as pleaſeth him, whom hartily I beſeeche for his ſonnes ſake, bleſſe vs with that bleſſing whiche hee gaue his Apostle, that in all places wee may bee vnto him in Ieſus Christ, a ſweete ſauour of life vnto life to all his ſaints with whom wee are. So ſhall I more gladlie walke all the wayes of his appointment, and you more willinglie beare with myne abſence, the will of God bee done in all thinges. When you are at Braye, if the Lorde will, I ſhalbe more quiet with you. In the meane time (good Maistres) ſo beleeue as you haue ſeene and hearde, and praye for me that I may liue to his glorie, who hath ſhewed me ſuch mercie, that I may ſay with the Prophet Dauid: <hi>What ſhall I giue a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine for all that he hath giuen mee?</hi> And ſo doe you reioyce in the bleſſing that GOD hath giuen you, that more and more your estate here may be a ſure te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of a more bleſſed hope, that ſhall one day bee reuealed, when honor and glorie ſhall ſucceed in the place of labour and ſorrowe that nowe aboundeth. The Lord bleſſe you and all yours, keepe you and giue you a plentifull bleſſing in his newe Testament, and in his kingdome, which is righteouſnes, and peace, and ioye in the holy Ghost, the glorie whereof ſhall not bee darkened, when the Sunne and Moone ſhall loſe their
<pb facs="tcp:178438:17"/> light, and faine men with deſire of it, that ſhall fill vs once with the countenance of the Lorde. A glorious hope in an earthly tabernacle, but a more glorious per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance in a heauenly creature, when we ſhalbe free from ſinne and death, and be made like vnto him that ſitteth at the right hande of maiestie and power. Which tyme the Lorde God fulfill in the goodnes of his pleaſure, for our ſoules hope: in whom we haue ſetled our hope. Commendations, &amp;c.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Maiſtres B.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lord Ieſus Christ bee with you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen. J am ſorie that hitherto I could not come vnto you, &amp; I would be more ſorie, if you ſhould thinke I had leuer be any where then in your houſe, I had thought ſhortly to haue come, and I felte my ſelfe ſomewhat ſtronge and able to trauell, but nowe on fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>day last the eleue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>th of this moneth, I had a feauer, and fiue or ſixe dayes after I felte it, and my ſtomacke is very ill euer ſince, and my cough much increaſeth. This is my health that God giueth me. But let him do his will, he is the God of life, and one day will aboliſhe theſe troubleſome thinges, and make vs feele health in immortalitie, and I beſeeche him for his Christes ſake to remember vs in his goodnes, that wee may knowe all his mercies, and then J am well aſſured both you and I, and all weake bodyes, ſhall ſo little care for the fray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie of theſe tabernacles, that we will reioyce in the remembrance of putting them of, to thinke that wee
<pb facs="tcp:178438:17"/> ſhall ſee and take holde of him that liueth euer, and will one day make theſe mortall bodyes, like vnto the glorious body of his beloued ſonne. This we knowe &amp; in this we are comforted: and holde it fast good Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſe B. euen as you will holde your happie dayes: for the hope of it ſhall not be confounded. but when all our enimies haue ſpentt their euill willes, and can doe no more hurt vnto vs, he ſhalbe on our right hande whom we haue looked for, and he ſhall call vs with that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed voyce, <hi>Come ye bleſſed of my Father.</hi> Let vs praye to vnderstande this, for it hath pleaſure &amp; ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectuall gladnes, more then all the faire countenances of the world, in which in deede there is nothinge but vanitie of vanities, and all is vanitie: and thinke good Mistreſſe B. howe many occaſions are before vs to cauſe vs to forget this, or to let the deſire of it, to be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> quenched in vs, or at the least to fill our ſelues with o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pleaſures of the worlde, but God ſhall keepe you from the corruptions of the worlde, and giue vnto you a wiſe heart, which euery daye may ſearche your thoughtes, and ſuffer you neuer to forget your latter ende: and ſeeing euery day doeth bring you neare vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to it, let euery day kindle more your affections, that you may loue it vnto the ende: and then our hope ſhalbe full, and our mouthes opened for euer, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Maiſtres B.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lorde Ieſus Christ be with you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer. As J trust the Lord doeth ſtrenghten you to
<pb facs="tcp:178438:18"/> better health, that you may liue to his prayſe, ſo J am deſirous to heare alſo of your amendment, but much more (as God hath made manifest in you many tokens of his grace) ſo J hartily pray that you may bee made euen as Paule to moorne ſtill in this earthlie taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, and to ſaye vnfainedlie, <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt:</hi> this is that good iſſue of life to which I haue often prayed that J might attayne vnto it: this is that meaſure of grace, whiche as I am most bounde, ſo hartely J beſeech our God and Sauiour, that it may plentifully be powred vppon you. And if wee ſhalbe made in our liues ſo happie, then haue we a dwelling in perfect peace: and in deede we be receyued into the couenaunt of the newe Testament, that wee ſhould be filled with ioye of the holy Ghost. For what can diſquiet vs, or what can bee grieuous vnto vs, if in the face of Ieſus Christ we ſee our riſing agayne from the graue, and feare not before the ſhaddow of death, all other afflictions they are but ministers vnto this, &amp; in the preſence of death they are disperſed, and they doe not followe vs vnto the darke places. If God will haue mercie vpon vs to bleſſe vs into this victorie, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hath hee giuen vs our inheritaunce in pleaſant places, and our portion in a happie lot. What ſo euer enimies are againſt vs, they ſhall ſtriue in vayne: and all things contrarie vnto vs, ſhall haue no ſtrength, for beyonde death there is no power in them, and death it ſelfe is diſpiſed in our eyes. Jf we felt not this in our heartes, but would ſeeke outwarde testimonie of men, let him ſpeake that findeth any greater feare then this. The ſicke perſon or priſoner may bee loth to dye, but the dead man he feareth no euill: and they that liue in
<pb facs="tcp:178438:18"/> prosperitie, this is not their feare least they ſhould haue a fall, but it is death that is bitter vnto all them that haue peace in their riches. Seeing this then is the greatest tyrant that maketh Princes tremble, and that anguiſh of harte that turneth all pleaſure into worm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woode, what ſoeuer is vnder the ſunne, good maistres B. as you are, ſo abyde: and as you haue receyued, ſo abounde till the good graces of the liuinge GOD haue made you ſtronger then ſinne or death: ſo ſhall your dayes be all in bleſſing, and your accounted tymes haue true delight till the latter ende doe ſhine in hope. So ſhall you bee bolde to ſaye with Dauid: <hi>Surely the Lord will deliuer me from the ſnare of the hunter, and from the noyſome peſtilence: I ſhall not bee a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frayde of the feare of the night, nor of the arrowe that flyeth in the day, nor of the peſtilence that wal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in the darkenes, nor of the plague that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyeth at noone: I haue ſet the moſt highe to bee my refuge, and there ſhall no euill come neare my tabernacle.</hi> The Lorde bleſſe vs in this good hope, &amp; make ſtronge our confidence in this perſwaſion, that at last we may dwell in ioye and gladnes: if feare haue often recourſe into our fraile bodyes, becauſe we carrie in vs corruption, whiche is the ſtrength of death, yet that feare ſhall not alwayes grieue vs, for our hope is perfect, and ſhall not be ſhaken. Wee ſhall goe but as Saint Paule, and Peter, Abraham and Jſaac haue gone before: and not onely they, but oure Fathers, our Mothers, and our dearest friendes are gone with them: and all that are behinde ſhall ouertake vs. The trouble of the trauell must needes appeare light in the middest of ſo happie companie: or if their loue haue
<pb facs="tcp:178438:19"/> not ſuch force in vs that Parentes and Friendes, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles, Prophetes, Patriarkes, and all the Saintes of God can make vs ſay, <hi>Let vs dye with the righteous, and let our latter ende bee as vnto them:</hi> yet ſure when among the dead I haue ſeene Christ, and in the graue haue founde the God of glorie, J ſhall ſay with a perfect hearte, <hi>Chriſt is my life, and death is myne aduantage.</hi> What then remayneth more vnto vs, but to ſtriue faithfullie that we may come vnto this, that God may worke with vs, as with his ſaintes, and wee may be pertaker with the happie Prophete, to ſee the louing kindnes of the Lorde, which is better then lyfe, and to ſaye with him: <hi>As the hart longeth after the water brookes, ſo my ſoule longeth to ſee the Lord:</hi> and in the meane ſeaſon that we yet fulfill our accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted tyme, whiche the Lorde graunt for his Churches ſake, that you may doe euen vntill olde age and many yeares, in good increaſe of your childrens children, &amp; happie peace of his choſen people. In the meane while I ſay, that your hope may be precious before you, and in this earthlie tabernacle, yet may haue your conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation in the highest heauen, from thence lookinge for a Sauiour, euen Ieſus Christ the righteous, who ſhall change this corruptible body, to make it like to his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious body, in that bleſſed time whiche ſhall ſkatter a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way all affliction, &amp; ſeale within that happie aſſura<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of immortalitie, whiche ſhalbe in the preſence of the God of glorie: when this weake body ſhall haue a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence (of a fewe ſorrowfull dayes) in euerlastinge righteouſnes. Jn whiche hope the Lorde graunt many yeares you may rest.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Yours Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <pb facs="tcp:178438:19"/>
               <head>To Maiſtres B.</head>
               <p>THe Lord who is riche in mercie, keepe vs euer in the aſſured couenant of his newe Teſtament made in Jeſus Chriſt, that we may feele the forgiuenes of our ſinnes, and reioyce in the hope of eternall life, Amen. I am ſure you wilbe gladde (good maiſtres B.) to heare of our ſafe comming home, And J would be gladde to heare of all your well dooing, at your Saint <hi>Ellins,</hi> &amp; therefore J writte vnto you, Both to heare agayne that God continueth his good bleſſinges towardes you, and to certifie you that (I thanke God) J am nowe ſafe at Shenfildes, I haue not yet taken the plaster, but this day J haue begonne to drinke Maistres P. Water. Let it haue the worke which God will: For in health our meate doe not nouriſhe vs, but by his worde. In ſickneſſe medicines can doe vs no good, except he bleſſe them. We haue no newes here to write of but of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trie thinges, ſcarſe worth the telling, and leſſe worſe the practiſinge of it could be amended, euery man go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after his Oxe and his horſe: and most doe glorifie God no more then their bruite beast. Jf they bee like vnto vs which are in the Court and in the Citie, that the one be as ambitious, the other as couetous as we bee brutiſhe, and God be forgotten of vs all alike, we may take vs againe the Lamentation of Ieremie: for it is the great mercies of God that we bee not conſumed. But if ſuch be the miſerie in the worlde, wee that are not of the worlde, but by Christ are taken out of the worlde: Let vs not loue the worlde which is ſuch an enemie vnto God, and then we ſhall not be condemned with the worlde when Christ ſhall come in glorie.
<pb facs="tcp:178438:20"/> And the Lord be prayſed, who hath giuen vs eyes to ſee and eares to heare, that we might bee wiſe harted: not to ſay peace and truce with ſuch things, with ſuch men crye peace and truce, but rather to haue our life hidden with Christ in God, and on his right hande be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holde the peace which paſſeth all vnderstandinge, and good Maiſtres B. increaſe in this, God hath giuen you a happie helper, who is willinglie ledde to all righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes: The Lord God make his good worke perfect for his ſonnes ſake, in him, in you, and in vs all that loue the comming of Jeſus Christ, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord</hi> Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter of Ed. Der. to Miſtres H.</head>
               <p>GRace and peace, &amp;c. I haue heard (good Maiſtres H.) of your heauie estate, that in many troubles the Lorde doeth exerciſe you, but I trust you are alſo taught to ſay alwayes before God, <hi>Thy will be done,</hi> and if this be your prayers, then knowe that nothinge happeneth but by his appointement, and be contented with all that he hath done, ſo that your heart may beare you witneſſe, that of all thinges the Lord is moſt deare vnto you: and for your troubles, giue onely your hearte to loue the Lorde, and they ſhall ſeeme neyther great nor ſtronge vnto you. For what can bee great, if our heart be prepared to ſay with Saint Paule, <hi>That we reioyce in afflictions, becauſe they ſhall breede in vs a hope which ſhall neuer make vs aſhamed:</hi> or what can be great, if God haue taught vs, <hi>That the momentaine afflictions of this worlde, they are not
<pb facs="tcp:178438:20"/> worthie of the glorie that ſhalbe reuealed vnto vs:</hi> or what can ſeeme great, if we heare the Apostle: <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren reioyce in afflictions, reioyce exceedingly: when you fall into many and great tribulations,</hi> Surely good Maistres H. all is nothing, for a frayle body, a ſhort life, a ſinfull creature, what can come vnto it that ſhould diſmay it: nay howe ſhould we not (if we knowe it well) bee glad, if death alſo were at our beddes ſide, that we might at once ſee the outmost malice of the diuell, and after for euermore bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered from him. A great cloude of witneſſes (as t'h A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postle ſayeth) are cited vnto in the eleuenth Chapter to the Hebrues, of which euery one ſhould bee our ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample to beare all croſſes that the Lord doeth ſende, knowing that he is delighted with vs, when wee bee faithfull to abyde theſe momentaine and light chastiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentes. <hi>Iob, Dauid, Paule,</hi> our Sauiour Christ him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, howe many things ſuffered they, howe are we not aſhamed to refuſe the cauſe which they haue borne, and way well your owne caſe what it is, and you ſhall ſee little cauſe of ſorrowe in it, or if you compare it with other, none at all. Hath your huſbande bene vnkinde vnto you, beare it, and you ſhall winne him at the last: if not, thanke God that you can continewe louing and obedient euen vnto an vnkinde huſbande. And I aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure you in this one vertue there is more comfort and ioye, then there can be griefe in all the diſcourteſies of men: and what is that croſſe of yours in reſpect of that which <hi>Abigaill</hi> did ſo longe and patientlie beare? But your ſonne hath grieued you much<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> yea but you haue not the hundreth parte of the griefe that Dauid might haue had for his ſonne <hi>Abſolon:</hi> and will you be more
<pb facs="tcp:178438:21"/> greeued then he? Your ſonne I trust, ſhall yet proue well, and you ſhall ſee his recouerie: if not, this maner of diſeaſe is rather a testimonie of a conſcience grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued with his euill doing, then an argument of his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, ſo that euen in this griefe you haue great cauſe of ioye: and what if God take from you the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort of one childe, leauing againe vnto you the comfort of a great many: Will you, or can you repine against the louing kindnes of the Lorde? Howe gladde would <hi>Dauid</hi> haue bene of other good children in the loſſe of one euill: yet you haue lost none, neither is your ſonne knowen to bee ſo euill, but you may reioyce in him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: yet if all things were as euill as you could ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, what then? Where is our loue to Ieſus Christe, that gaue his precious body to the death for our ſinnes? If we will not leaue ſonne, daughter, and our own life for his ſake, can one heare fall from your ſonnes heade but at Christes commaundement? Is not he head of his Church, and all thinges happen they not vnto vs as he will? Herein you ſhall knowe you loue God aboue all, when you can forget the childe of your wombe, for his ſake. And therefore (good Maistres H.) giue not your ſelfe to any inordinate affections to offende God, and hurt your ſelfe, but ſay and thinke, <hi>Thy will bee done, O Lorde,</hi> and when the time ſhall come of our latter ende, we ſhall neuer haue ende of the bleſſed life which God ſhall giue vnto you, and to all his ſaintes in that day. Thus in haste I am constrayned to ceaſe to write, but I will not ceaſſe to pray, that God may bleſſe you, and giue you his ioyfull Spirite, to fill you with all ſpirituall comfort, against the tentations of the worlde, and all the enuie of the Diuell. And pray
<pb facs="tcp:178438:21"/> for me I beſeech you, that I may account all the world to be but donge<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the ende I may winne Ieſus Christ, (to whom) the liuing and eternall God I committ you for euer, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>The xix. of Aprill.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord Ieſus, the onely forgiuenes of all our ſinnes,</hi> Edward Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Letters of Ed. De. to Miſtres K.</head>
               <p>THe Lord God direct vs with his holy ſpirite, that we may loue and feare him vnto the ende, Amen. Jt greeueth me good Maistres K. that you ſhould bee ſo longe at <hi>Hendon</hi> as nowe you haue bene, and all this while I could finde no leyſure to come vnto you, &amp; whatſoeuer my faulte hath bene herein, I will make no other excuſe, but deſire you to forgiue it. And I pray God though I ſee you not, yet I may ſo remember you, as J am bounde, and ſo my not comminge vnto you ſhall greeue me the leſſe. Nowe touchinge your owne caſe, I knowe you are wyſe to ſee, that the Lord giueth you newe instructions to be wiſe in him, and to giue ouer your ſelfe vnto him. For as God hath bleſſed you many wayes, and giuen you a good callinge in the worlde, So he viſiteth you euery day, and humbleth you with many chastiſementes before him. God hath giuen you huſbande, children, famelie, and other bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings, but you enioye none of them without a croſſe, ſometime one thing, ſometime another, and commonly your owne weake and ſicklie body makes you that you can not haue your ioye as you would. Yea J doubt not,
<pb facs="tcp:178438:22"/> but it is ſo abridged vnto you, that ſometime it grieueth you that you cannot eyther haue care ouer your houſe, as you wiſhe, or attende on your children as you deſire, or reioyce with your huſbande, as otherwiſe you might. But this griefe God recompenceth with great benefite, for our Sauiour Christ is our good warrant, that this is the lot of Gods ſaintes, to enioye his bleſſinges with afflictions, ſo that the more that you bee ſorrowſull, the more you be ſure that the liuing God hath giuen you your portion: And ſo your ſorrowe is ioye vnto you. Beſides this, the mingling of your ioye with ſorrowe, and wealth with woe, is a happie tempringe vnto you of heauen with earth, that you ſhould neither loue nor rest in this, aboue that which is meete, but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, all is but vanitie, ſo loue it as tranſitorie things, and haue your great delight with the Lord alone, who is vnto you health, prosperitie, ioye, and eternall life. This good Maistres K. you knowe, but yet this I alſo put you in minde of for though God haue bleſſed you, yet you are but a weake woman, and haue neede (in the common frayeltie of mans nature) to be ſtirred vp with exhortatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Remember therefore euer that which is the ende of all, <hi>Feare God, and keepe his comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dements.</hi> For this is the whole ſcope of our life, which when we haue brought to his appointed ende, wee ſhall ſee the hope, which we haue long looked for: and when immortalitie hath brought happines into light, and ſcattered away our feare, we ſhall ſaye then, <hi>Bleſſed be the daye in whiche firſte wee learned to feare the Lorde.</hi> And the Lorde bleſſe you with his holy ſpirit, that you may in the middest of other care, haue plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in this, and in other ſorrowe reioyce in the Lord,
<pb facs="tcp:178438:22"/> and alwayes reioyce. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende me J pray you, to your litle ones, <hi>Nan, Beſſe,</hi> and <hi>Marie,</hi> And the Lord make you and maister K. gladde parentes of good children, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Tobie,</hi> 
                     <date>the last of Februarie <hi>1575.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord Ieſus,</hi> Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Maiſtres K.</head>
               <p>THe grace of our Lord Ieſu Christ bee with you e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer, Amen. I thanke you good Maistres K. for your letter and for your medicine, and for your good will to him to whom you before did owe ſo little. Tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching my diſeaſe, I did ſoddainlie cogh and ſpit much bloud, ſo that when with much forcing my ſelfe, I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>frained, it ratteled in my throte, as if I had bene a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: next day in the like ſorte J did, and once ſince the taking of theſe medicines for the ſtaying of it, it is nowe ſtayed, but J feele a great ſtopping of my winde, and much prouocation to coughe, whiche if I did, J ſhould ſpit bloud as before. I pray you aſke your Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſicion what he thinketh good to bee done. And good Maistres K. against all diſeaſes and ſickneſſes of the body, doe as you doe, and increaſe it with an vnfay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned testimonie of your owne heart. Committ your health, your ſickenes, your body, your ſoule, your life, and your death, to him that died for vs, and is riſen againe. A ſicke body with ſuch an ayde, hath greater treaſure then the Queenes Iewell-houſe. Praye ſtill, and pray for me. J ſee the goodnes of God ſuch to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardes me, as (I thanke God) except ſinne, I waighe not all the worlde a f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ather: and with as a gladde a
<pb facs="tcp:178438:23"/> minde I ſpitt bloud, (I trust) as cleare ſpitle. To thoſe that loue God, all thinges are for the best: hee hath a harde heart that beleeueth not this. For the Church, I commit it to the Lorde: the Lorde graunt with that affection that I owe vnto it, and for all my labour in it (I thanke God) I am guiltie neither of couetouſnes, nor ambitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but as God hath giuen me grace, J ſought onely his glorie. J write this vnto you good Maistres K. becauſe you knowe it, and that you may the more effectuallie remember him, that will knowe you when the worlde, your health, your corruptihle bodie, death and ſinne it ſelf, haue done their worſte. Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mende me to Maister K. your little ones, to Maister R. The Lorde bleſſe vs all, that we make our bodies ſhake, &amp; not our bodies vs.</p>
               <closer>
                  <salute>Vale in Chriſto Ieſu.</salute>
                  <dateline>
                     <date>
                        <hi>25.</hi> Iul. <hi>1575.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Tuus in Chriſto</hi> Ed. Dering.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Maiſtres K.</head>
               <p>TTe Lord God who ſheweth mercie to whom hee will ſhewe mercie, and haue compaſſion on whom he will haue compaſſion, accordinge to his loue with which he loued vs before the worlde was made, looke vpon vs, and leade vs in our wayes, that in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes and holines, peace and ioye of the holy Ghost, wee may finiſhe our compas and come vnto him, Amen. If I could, good Maistres K. doe as J ſhould, then my wayes were perfect among men, but it is with mee as with manie other, ſmall hinderances to an vnwillinge minde, are occaſions great enough to keepe vs from doing well. This hath made me to pretermitt manie
<pb facs="tcp:178438:23"/> dueties which had bene better done. And J dare not make anie other excuſe why J haue not written vnto you oftener: for though I haue in a wearie bodie many thinges to doe, and could make excuſes whiche you would eaſilie beleeue, yet ſure I am, if ſlought and negligence were vtterlie gone, a fewe lines were ſo ſoone written, that J could not want time for ſo little labour, this is true, <hi>&amp; ſit erranti medicina confeſſio.</hi> Touching my ſicknes, hee that ſent it he doeth rule it, and as he will ſo farre let it goe. J feele yet difficultie of breath and coughinge: and I ſee palenes and leanes abyding ſtill, yet I thanke God I am ſo well, as wee ſuppoſed all to haue ſeene you at <hi>Henden</hi> this next Monday, but God hath changed our waye, and by oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion we haue differred it, trusting yet to ſee you ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie ſhortlie, if the Lord will, to whom we commit both your wayes and ours. And nowe good Maistres K. further J neede not write vnto you, for whiche cauſe yet especiallie you craue my letters, I knowe whom you haue beleeued, vpon what grounde you ſtande, who hath ſealed your perſwaſion in you, he is able to keepe that you haue committed vnto him, euen vntill that day, that the things of the worlde are changed before vs all. Affliction may be great and make vs murmur, prosperitie may abounde and make vs proude, the worlde may fill our eyes and our eares, that ſometime we may be blinde and not ſee our hope, our owne con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcence may peraduenture ſtinge vs that wee for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gett the good workes wherein wee had delight, but the councell of the Highest ſtandeth fast for euer: the Lord knoweth all that are his. Jn this tower of defence our dwelling is made for vs, and the gates of hell ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:178438:24"/> not preuaile against vs. When wee ſinne, wee must needes be ſorrowfull, and to offende ſuch a Sauiour, it will greeue vs more then death it ſelfe: but to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber againe ſo aſſured hope, we can not but reioyce in the Lorde, and alwayes reioyce. Thus I leaue you to your owne hearte, where is your ſtrong ſafetie: and to your ſecrete thoughtes, which comfort you in the night. And committing my ſelfe vnto your prayers, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeche God the Father of our Lorde Ieſus Christe, to keepe you and yours. Commende me to your little ones: pardon me for writing in ſuch piece of paper, J could hardlie gett this. Maister H. and my wife wiſhe to ſee you. The Lord keepe vs vnblameable in his ſight.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From <hi>Tobye,</hi> 
                     <date>the xiiij. of August, <hi>1575.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Your bounden in the Lord,</hi> Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>To Maiſtres K.</head>
               <p>THe Lord God direct vs in all our wayes, that they may bee vnblameable in his ſight, and our faith may be ſtrenghtened in the bleſſed hope of his elect, ſo that nothing be able to ſhake it from henceforth, from the boldnes and aſſurance of eternall life. Many and iust cauſes good Maistres K. haue kept mee, ſo that theſe holy dayes I could not ſee you, but I knowe no excuſe why I could not write vnto you: and therfore for the one as I am ſure you doe willinglie pardon me, ſo the other I beſeeche you to except, both as a testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie of my minde that I forget you not, and as a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of that duetie J owe vnto you: for if I ſhould not faithfullie remember you, though you had other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe
<pb facs="tcp:178438:24"/> done nothing for me, yet I were vnworthie of ſo much good will. And if I ſhould not as in bounden duetie be most carefull to ſtrenghten and comfort that good purpoſe; whiche your ſelfe haue choſen for the curſe of your life, I were not worthie of the acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of the ſaintes of God. Therefore departing from <hi>London</hi> againe (as J could not chuſe) I haue yet writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vnto you, as I must needes: And I hartelie praye that God may increaſe his goodnes in you, and earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie beſeech you, as you haue receyued that, ſo you would abounde more and more, a ſhort request and ſoone hearde: but exceeding difficult to ſome to practize, &amp; yet not difficult vnto you, but eaſie and light, as you can deſire, for he that is borne of God ouercommeth the worlde. And the anointing (as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſaieth) which you haue receyued of God, dwelleth in you, and you neede not that any man teach you, but as the ſame anointing teacheth you all thinges, and it is true and not lyinge, and as it is taught you, you ſhall abyde in it. Maruell not that J write this vnto you, nor be vnwillinglie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected to heare of your owne happineſſe. Jt is (as <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſayeth) an other mans mouth that prayſeth you and not your owne, and what neede you feare. And I ſpeake not deceitfullie, which J thanke God J hate, nor giue I titles, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſayeth, which the Lorde doeth ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre. But ſeeing (as I am perſwaded) that in you, which Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> could ſee in the people to whom hee wrote and to whom he gaue ſo honorable prayſe: why ſhould not J be bolde vpon ſo good warrant to ſay alſo vnto you: You are the Lordes: and God who iustified then his Apostles wordes, he will iustifie them nowe and euer, for he is mercifull without ende. Lett vs not
<pb facs="tcp:178438:25"/> then good Maistres K. bee hencefoorth ſorrowfull or faint hearted: Paule and Peter, and all tht Apostles and Prophetes haue ſpoken glorious thinges vnto vs, and we will beleeue them. And yet not they, but the ſpirit of God hath giuen vs this testimonie, and it is true. For what were the <hi>Romaynes, Corinthians, Galathians,</hi> and all other whome the Spirite nameth Saintes and Holy ones, were they not as wee? Fraile and weake as wee, and our faith as theirs? But wee feele a great deale of infirmitie in our ſelues, did not they ſo, and did not the ſpirit of God ſee more in them, then them ſelues could feele? yet it calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſaintes: yea and ſo it calleth vs, that wee ſhould not feare: and therefore as I ſaide, I ſaye agayne, you are anoynted of the Lorde, and you ſhall not fall, if your heart beare you witneſſe, that the profeſſion which you make, is vnfained in you, as I am ſure it beareth you witneſſe. One care onelie wee haue, which alſo wee will haue vnto the ende: and that is, that we may glorifie him, who hath glorified vs. Jn this doing, as I accuſe my ſelfe most aboue all other men, ſo J prayſe not you a white. For J knowe good Maistres K. herein you are too too faultie, and ſo is all fleſhe: our fleſhe, the world, and the Deuill, they are to ſtronge for vs, but bleſſed bee the Lorde God, who hath giuen vs victorie in Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ, and wee will doe if God giue vs grace, as his Apostles did, wee will chastiſe our bodyes, and bringe them in ſubiection, that all that knowe our re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, ſhall not blame our workes: And I thanke God for all that you haue obteyned: And I beſeeche you increaſe and abounde more, that as hee will giue vs a full rewarde, ſo wee may offer vp our bodyes a
<pb facs="tcp:178438:25"/> holy ſacrifice, to prayſe his name, who hath had mercie vppon vs. And pray for me, that my handes &amp; tonge may ioyne in the workes of Gods Saintes: and let vs all growe togither vnto that bleſſed hope, till wee haue founde that happie ſtre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ght, by which the world is cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified vnto vs, and wee vnto the worlde: But the Lord that teacheth you, to him I leaue you: whom I beſeech to open your eies into ſo large &amp; wyde a ſpiritual ſight, that you may yet more clearlie ſee and feele the glorie of God &amp; immortalitie. Fare well good Maistres K. Commende mee to Nan, Beſſe, Marie. The Lorde bleſſe you with them euer, Amen.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Tuus in Chriſto,</hi> Edwardus Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter of M. Ed. De. to the Ladie G.</head>
               <p>¶ <hi>The grace of our Lorde Ieſu Chriſt, bee with you euer,</hi> Amen. JF either I might doe the duetie wherevnto your well deſeruing hath bound me, or might requite with thanks that with all your good wil you haue deſerued: I knowe and confeſſe it (good Madame) longe ſince I ſhould haue come to ſee you: but ſuch is my caſe as I cannot doe either what is most meete, or what I most deſire: for ſometimes by buſines &amp; ſometime by ſicknes, &amp; ſometime by opportunity of others, I am holde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> here, that J could neuer yet haue opportunitie to ryde fare, or to ſee my natiue Countrie &amp; nighest friendes. Once in So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer J would haue gone to M. B. beſides Windſore and the ſeconde night of my trauell, J could not ſleape, but taried a ſeuen night in the ſame place, &amp; then came backe againe, ill at eaſe: thus it pleaſeth God to deale with me, and ſuch a body he hath giuen me, to the ende
<pb facs="tcp:178438:26"/> (I am ſure) J ſhould not loue this preſent vanitie, but remember him that liueth euer, <hi>&amp; deſire to bee diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued to ſee his glorie.</hi> And this I beſeeche you thinke to be the only cauſe, that I haue not of longe time ſeene you and others, with whom otherwiſe I would wiſhe to dwell: and if it bee the good will of God to prosper my iourneys in time conuenient, J trust to ſee you oftener hereafter: but his will bee done, who appoynteth our wayes, and numbreth our ſteppes, and doeth all things for the best to thoſe that loue him, and to him if J can commit you in my daily prayers, that ſo my ſpirit bee preſent with you, how longe ſoeuer J be abſent in body, yet my duetie I owe you, ſhall not bee altogither vnper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, and that piece of it which yet is wantinge, that in daily exhortation J might (by the grace of God) ſtirre vp your minde, that in the meane time let me ſupplie with theſe letters: In which moſt hartily I beſeech you (good Madame) goe on forwarde, and faint not in the courſe of godlines, increaſe ſtil in faith, in loue, in hope til with a wiſe hart you haue ſuch a feeling of the glory of God, &amp; of eternall life, that you haue made your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count vp with the world, &amp; are at a point with all that is vnder the Sun. While God ſhall prolong your dayes, reioyce in him that hath giuen you life, and vſe all his gifts to his glory: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his appointed time ſhal come and bring death into your doores: let this be the prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of your heart, <hi>you deſire to be looſed &amp; to bee with Chriſt,</hi> and let this be the anſwere of your tongue, <hi>Lord nowe letteſt thou thy ſeruant departe in peace.</hi> Surelie then it ſhall come vnto you, that a happie life ſhal haue a bleſſed end. Your former times haue found their wiſhed iſſue, &amp; the entrance of your graue, ſhalbe
<pb facs="tcp:178438:26"/> the beginninge of your glorie: Hee hath ſpoken it that can not deceyue vs, <hi>That euerie one that beleeueth in him ſhall not taſte of death, but ſhall paſſe from death to life.</hi> This (good Madame) is the crowne &amp; garlande of all our pleaſures: reioyce in feeling it, and be glad in louing it, knit it faste to all the thoughtes of your hart, &amp; neuer forget it, it ſhal giue you more plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in one day of your life, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> without it you can find in a thouſande yeares: and all the men of the worlde which feele their pleaſure in this life, &amp; know nothing better, then to followe their owne concupiſcence, they ſhall periſh when you ſhall abyde, &amp; they ſhall mourne when you ſhall reioyce, becauſe they haue forgotten the liuinge God whom you haue loued: Manie tentations ſhalbe continuallie against you, but God is able to ſet you free from them: cast your care on him, &amp; you haue wonne the victorie. And to the ende you may knowe him, &amp; how to truſt in him, as the Prophet Dauid did ſo let vs doe, that is: Let vs make his teſtimonies to be our delight, &amp; excerciſe our ſelues in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> day &amp; night, for they onely can make vs wiſe, and renue in vs the image of God, that we may be perfect as our heauenlie father is perfect. This hope J thanke God hath bine before me, that J haue not feared in any trouble: and in a good conſcience of this doing, I had rather haue the displeaſure of the worlde, then with loſſe of this deſire or any hurt of it, to winne the fauour of all mortall men. And ſo I am ſure it ſhall be with you that day, in which you ſhall ſo feele Gods glorie, &amp; eternall life, that you will conſecrate your life for euer vnto him, loue hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> feare him, longe after him: Jt ſhal be more ioyfull vnto your the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the daie of your birth, &amp; your heart ſhal be ſee
<pb facs="tcp:178438:27"/> as Saint Paule ſaith, <hi>to vſe the world as though you vſed it not:</hi> not to forſake the world or worldly things, (for they are the gifts of god for the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte of our life) but as though wee forſaked it, ſo let our loue bee taken from it, and be euer with him who is the giuer of all, &amp; hath all immortalitie. There is not a day that paſſeth ouer our heades, but it afflicteth the body, &amp; maketh it a day ſhorter liuing then it was: Let there not be a day but ſhall ſtrenghthen our faith, that we may be glad we are one daie neerer the preſence of our God, then wee were before. And I beſeech god (who only can do what he will) worke his good will with you in all ſpirituall bleſſings, that you may abounde: and in the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dition of this life that you may reioice, till your accounted times bee all fulfilled. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours in the Lord Ieſu,</hi> Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter of M. Ed. De. to the Ladie M.</head>
               <p>THE Lorde God who hath onely power to worke his will, and hath ſhewed mercy vnto vs in an eternall couenant, make vs perfect in all our ways to abound in righteouſnes, and loue his glorie, that in life and death we may be happie, and haue ioy in his preſence, who li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth euer, Amen. Good Madame, tbe dutie that J haue long owed vnto you, doth much binde me: &amp; the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of your good inclination, ſufficientlie doth em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boulden me to write at this time vnto you: and J truſt the Lord God who hath giuen you his grace, and called me to this worke, will bleſſe the labour that it may bee profitable to his glorie &amp; your co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort. For if his worde haue ſo great ſtrength in his Saintes when they are yet
<pb facs="tcp:178438:27"/> vnbeleeuing and ignorant, that it reuealeth euen the ſecretes of their hartes, that it maketh them fall down to worſhip him and to acknowledge his mightie power in it: J am ſure it can not be but the ſame worde ſhall haue ſtrength in you, wholy &amp; altogither to conſecrate your ſelfe vnto the Lord, till all your delight be in him alone. So that I am nowe, more to praye for my ſelfe then for you, that I may rather ſpeake the trueth then you heare it: for of this I am ſure your heart is prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red (as the Prophete ſayth) to a good purpoſe, the Lord make my hande as the penne of a good writer. And nowe (good Madame) this is the ſumme of all, Feare God &amp; loue him: your goods, your credit, your thoghts, your deſires, your body, your life, giue it all vnto him, that he only may pleaſe you, nothing but he only delight you, his worde inſtruct you, his wil perſwade you, that whether you liue or whether you die you may be wholy his: A ſhort leſſon &amp; ſoone learned, harde J confeſſe of the worlde to practiſe, but not harde to you whom God hath loued: for what is it can call away your deſire, that wholy and altogither it ſhould not be in this? Jt is onely the worlde that hath taken vp enimitie against vs, and ſtriueth dailie to ſeparate vs from the Lorde. But what is in the worlde why the perſwaſions of it ſhould pleaſe vs? especiallie you who haue had expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of it, whoſe life God hath filled with worldlie things. You knowe what is the comfort of houſes and landes: you haue weighed them well and found them light. You knowe the gladnes of a mother, and haue in your ſight So<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nes &amp; Daughters, the triall of it is in you, &amp; hath entred deepe, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> as they haue bin the fruite of your owne wombe: but in them you haue no ſuch ioye
<pb facs="tcp:178438:28"/> as in the ſpirit of adoption, by which you knowe your ſelfe to be the childe of God. You knowe the treaſure of a good huſband, with whom you haue had peaceable and louinge dayes: but howe much is it a greater ioye of vnspeakeable gladnes to feele your ſelfe ioyned to Jeſus Christ, &amp; made a chaste member of his glorious body with whom you ſhalbe ioyned for euer. You haue ſeene a great many yeares of the age of man, and haue meaſured the length of them, ſo that if you might liue the dayes of Abraham, yet you might account your houres and ſee the time at hande, when in the ende of your courſe you ſhall take your rest: and what were this to immortalitie. To be ſhort and to pretermit ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie things wherewith God hath made your life as a bleſſing, you haue ſeene fauour, Credite, Landes, Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie, Friendes, Seruauntes: the pleaſures of theſe God hath giuen you. You haue ſeene fulneſſe of ſuch delights: but this and all els that you haue ſeene what is it to the grace of God, the fellowſhippe of Saintes, the forgiuenes of your ſinnes, the loue of his countenance, the aſſurance of your life, the brightnes of his glorie, &amp; your eternall bleſſinges. Sith then in the world is no ſure refuge, the more I haue ſeene the fruit of your faith, the more aſſuredlie J knowe the constancie of your minde readie to leaue the worlde to approch nearer vnto God, and to account all theſe thinges to be but dunge, to the ende you may winne Ieſus Christ, in whom you ſhalbe ſo much more bleſſed, as light is more bright then dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, health is more excellent then ſickneſſe, and life more precious then cruell death. This (good Madame) you haue long knowen, and with prayſe profeſſed it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong men: And nowe especiallie reape the fruite of it
<pb facs="tcp:178438:28"/> in theſe dayes of Gods viſitation, in which in a weake body you haue had a ſharpe ſickeneſſe, to teach you that your life is in the handes of God, &amp; the nature of your body that it is but dust, ſo that you ſhould not loue it but in the Lorde, nor be pleaſed with it but as it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth him, readie to laye it downe when he ſhall call you. This is that great and high commandement: <hi>To loue God aboue all,</hi> and this is the greatest obedience re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of man, to be readie to dye at the will of God: <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto which commaundement when I doe beſeech you willinglie to yeelde, I feele in my ſelfe howe the nature of man ſtriueth against it: all thoſe delightes of which I ſpake before (the pleaſures of this preſent life) they ariſe against it: although we had no other comfort, yet life it ſelf is ſweete vnto vs, &amp; we are loth to make our beds in the darke, our eyes they would yet ſee the ſunne, our eares would heare the ſounde of worldly elements, though our fleſhe be graſſe, yet graſſe hath a flower, &amp; our fraile bodyes haue vaniſhinge fantaſies agreeable vnto them as earth vnto earth, and from which most hardlie you ſhall pull it away, the Patriarkes &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phetes were ſometime afraide, Paule and Peter were not alwayes bolde, they loued euer that life which they ſawe in hope, but they did feele the death whichc did fight in their members: And howe ſhould I then ſaye vnto you a weake woman, feare not death, or if I ſay it howe can you performe it beeing ſo weake a veſſell of fleſhe and bloud: yet good Madame, giue me leaue to intreate you &amp; J hope you ſhall haue a heart to graunt it: J most humblie beſeeche you, feare not death. The Apostles were men as we are, yet Paule obteyned at last to be diſſolued &amp; be with Christ: if we be weaker
<pb facs="tcp:178438:29"/> then he, the graces of God ſhalbe more exalted in vs, and we alſo ſhall ſay at the last, <hi>Let thy ſeruaunt O Lord departe in peace:</hi> It is the Lorde that hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed this bleſſing vnto vs, let vs heare it with faith, and it will make death vile in our eyes: it is enough if we knowe God will giue this victorie to his people, lett vs be bolde, though we feare a litle while, yet feare ſhall be cast out, and we ſhall ſay with a free ſpirit, O death where is thy ſtinge, &amp;c. trie your ſelfe therefore euery day, and if your harte be bolde, reioyce good Madame, &amp; reioyce for euer: the last and greateſt enimie (which is death) is troden vnder your feete, and what els can hurt you: all other things of the world they are but ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes of death, and ſerue to make his power more fearfull vnto vs, friendes or kinſefolke, golde, ſiluer. pretious ſtones or al other pleaſures, all labour vnto one ende, to make vs more loth to die: vanquiſh death and you haue va<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>quiſhed all, height &amp; depth, life and death, all is yours, &amp; you are Chriſtes. And ſee I beſeeeh you what glorie you haue gotten, you are but a weake and ſicke woman whom God hath ſhut vp into your cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and tyed to your bedde: and yet the great tyrant of the world, that holdeth in bondage Kings &amp; Princes, and woundeth them all with feare &amp; terror, he is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded before you, &amp; the Lord of life he hath cruſhed him in pieces vnder you. A bleſſed day that brought you first into this battell, a bleſſed ſickeneſſe that made you endure the fight, &amp; moſt bleſſed ende in which you get the victorie: for who hath giuen you this ſtrength, or who raigneth in you in ſuch a day, but he who hath ſaied and done it, <hi>O death I wil be thy death:</hi> and if he be in you who hath aboliſhed death, and in whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:178438:29"/> ſight death ſhall neuer haue any rule, what treaſure, what depth of ioy and gladnes ſhall he bring with him: while you liue you ſhal liue in him, &amp; no man ſhall take your ioy from you: and whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you die you ſhall die in him, and death ſhalbe no death, but you ſhall paſſe to eternall life: and all that is fearfull ſhalbe farre from you: the burthen of ſinne, the malice of the deuill, the terrour of hell: the dreadfull words, goe ye curſed into eternall fire: All this is aboliſhed &amp; troden down in the croſſe of Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, who reigneth in you, &amp; giueth you his ſpirit, that you feare not death: and all things that fill with ioy not the earth onely, but the heauens alſo (you haue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed death) you ſhall feele the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all within you: the fel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowſhip of Saints &amp; Angels, the forgiuenes of ſinns, the reſurrection of the body, the life euerlasting, and the God of glorie: your eyes lightened with a pure faith ſhall ſee theſe things in ſo perfect beautie, that you ſhall caſt out death &amp; the feare of it: yea you ſhould thinke your time wearines if your dayes ſhould be prolonged, and you ſhould bee yet many yeares a ſoiorner in this bodie, in which you are a ſtraunger from the preſence of the Lorde: And the nearer your time approcheth, the gladder you ſhalbe of the ende of your iourney, when your harte ſhall feele it: And when the earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie houſe of this tabernacle ſhalbe deſtroyed, you haue a building giuen of God, a houſe not made with hands, but eternall in the heauens. In this faith you ſhall not onely not feare death, but you ſhall ſigh and moane (as Paule ſaith) till you ſee your glorie, and the lot of the ſaints that is in light, where there is no more ſorrow nor care, nor feare, nor death, but the God of all mercie, and father of our lord Jeſus Chriſt ſhalbe before vs for euer.
<pb facs="tcp:178438:30"/> Thus Madame (as my duetie is) J haue written vnto you, and God will bleſſe it as his promiſe is, that it ſhall be for the beſt, &amp; in the wiſdome of his word we ſhalbe ſtrengthned in his grace, that death &amp; ſickneſſe ſhalbe forgotten, &amp; all the deſirs of our heart ſhalbe with him. And the Lord God for his Sonnes ſake, ſo haue mercie vpon vs, that all euill taken from vs, we may reioyce in him, and ſee his bleſſed age that is in immortality, &amp; is ſealed in our heartes with his bleſſed ſpirit: To whom be glorie for euermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From Saint Ellens, <date>the tenth of Ianuarie, <hi>Anno Domini, 1576.</hi>
                     </date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Yours bounden in the Lord Ieſu, the onely forgiuenes of all our ſinnes,</hi> Ed. Deringe.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>A Letter written by M. Edward Deringe, to his Lord &amp; Maiſter the Duke of Northfolke.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Gratia et pax a Deo patre, et domino noſtro Ieſu Chriſto.</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>THE longe good will that I haue borne vnto you, as to one that earnestlie profeſſed the Goſpell, and the great duetie I owe vnto you as to my Lord &amp; Maſter, make, that nowe I ſhould write vnto you, not knowing whether opportunitie ſhalbe ſuch that hereafter J may doe you any ſeruice. God the author of all life he hath ſhutte both you and me vp in his handes: that there is great likelihood, our liues in this worlde they are but ſhort. The Prince that executeth the iudgement of the Lord, ſhe hath found you out in your great ſinnes: and ſickenes that raigneth ouer all fleſhe, it hath taken now longe holde vpon me. So that as I ſaide, we are both in the handes of the Lord, we are ſummoned paremtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, death hath giuen an aſſault, and the weake holdes of our life they are violentlie ſhaken. Nowe therefore
<pb facs="tcp:178438:30"/> my good Lord, let it vs take counſell togither, and as a wiſe Maister, learne of a faithfull ſeruaunt what is best to be done: the worst that our ſinnes can doe vnto vs, is to lay vpon vs the iust rewarde of death, my diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe which thus afflicteth me for many thouſand ſinns, it can but take away my life which J haue ſo abuſed. And all your deepe diſſimulation and hypocriſie, your great ambitions, your faithleſſe religion, which haue ſo bewitched you, what can they doe more then this? The remedie nowe is to make of neceſſitie a vertue, that is, to beare it wiſely, which you must needes abide. J haue (I thanke God) founde that grace, that I can loue this ſaying, <hi>Cupio diſſolui &amp; eſſe cum Chriſto,</hi> the Lord alſo open your hearte and guide your vnderstandinge, that with all ſaintes you may doe likewiſe, and praye, <hi>Veni Domine Ieſu.</hi> And now for aſmuch as this is the last duetie, that J am like to doe vnto you, as God ſhall giue grace I will ſo aduice you as I may testifie myne owne faith, and make you ſtrong against the daye of triall: trusting that our God ſhall ſo remember vs both in mercie, that after a little while we ſhall ſee better dayes, and raigne with him that abideth King for euer. There is now but one thing neceſſarie for you to learne in this life, that is, how you may willinglie deſire to die: a hard leſſon for a natural ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for death is our laſt eni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie &amp; his aſſault moſt violent to the triall of our faith: but Christ who hath ouercome death and hell, hee hath broken the ſtrength of this battell, and ſet vp the ſonges of triumph vnto all that beleeue, that we may haue the fulneſſe of ioy and ſay with gladnes, <hi>ô death where is thy ſting.</hi> Nowe that this ioye may be yours, and this gladnes your inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, prepare your ſelfe, not in your
<pb facs="tcp:178438:31"/> own wiſdo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, for that hath alredie deceiued you, but in the wiſdome of god, that your hope may be ſure. Jf you will now haue the hart that ſhal co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demne the force of death co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſider wherfore you are called to die: It is laid to your charg, that you haue delt traytrouſly with your Prince, with your cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>try, &amp; with the religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God: and vpon theſe crimes you are co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>demned to die. If you be guiltles, ô my Lord bleſſed are you, &amp; bleſſed is your portion: he hath ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> it that neuer will change: Jf whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you do well you ſuffer wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gfully, take it patie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, for this is accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to god: but if you be guilty you haue not your hope in death (for that you haue deſerued) but your hope is this, that you die ſo as it beco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth you: which if god ſhal gra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vnto you, then bleſſed is the howre that God ſhall bring vpon you, you ſhal make that change, which god for his Chriſtes ſake, lay ſpeedily vpon all his children, &amp; you ſhal die once, that you may liue euer. Now that you may know how you ought to die: learne this of the lord which he hath ſo plainly taught you. The firſt part of your true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce, muſt be an hu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ble co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: what ſoeuer your own conſcience can vtter more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is reuealed. O my Lorde ſpeake ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly the trueth, ſathan is enimie vnto vs &amp; his ſlightes are many: if you will treade the malicious ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent vnder your feete, &amp; triumph with Chriſt who hath ſpoiled hell, tell the trueth my Lord, conceale nothing, ſo ſhall you ſhunne the diuel. If my words ſeeme but light to perſwade you, heare the wiſeſt counſellour that euer raigned in Iſrael: He that hideth his ſinne (ſaieth Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon) ſhall neuer proſper, but he that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſeth &amp; forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth them, ſhall finde mercie. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Acan had tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in Iſrael &amp; deſerued death, when he was brought into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, Ioſhua ſaid vnto him, My Son J beſeech thee, giue glory to the lord God of Iſrael, make co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion
<pb facs="tcp:178438:31"/> vnto him, &amp; ſhew me now what thou haſt done. Loe my Lord, this is to giue glorie vnto God: to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe your ſin, &amp; tell what you haue done. The good king Dauid whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he had deſerued death, &amp; feared greatly the ſentence of the Prophet, he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed gladly &amp; made it knowen vnto the world what his ſin was, &amp; wherin he had offended. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God gaue his lawes vnto Iſrael, &amp; in the bloud of goates &amp; calues ſheweth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that was in Chriſt Jeſus: He ſo ordeined, that before their forgiuenes was preached, the high prieſt ſhould proclaime openlie what were the ſins of the people, &amp; ſo lay their ſins vpon the beaſtes. So ſtandeth it nowe with vs, if we will finde forgiuenes of our ſins, let vs caſt off the cloaks of ſhame, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe before heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, what we haue ſinned &amp; what we haue done. What greater perſwaſions can you yet require, or how can you thinke to pleaſe God if you wil hide your ſins? That was the practiſe of old Adam, but you are borne anew: that was the ſin of Cain, but you my good Lord are of a better kinred. Speak the truth &amp; ſhrinke not, God will once reueale the ſecrets of harts, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you ſhal reioice that ther is nothing of yours hid: fie vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſin, that you ſhould turn away for one houre &amp; receiue hereafter euerlaſting co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fuſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: better a thouſa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d times to receiue the reproch of fleſh, &amp; after receiue your glory of the Lord. Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> John Baptiſt preached firſt the Goſpell, he bpatized no more the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſuch as confeſſed their ſins. The loſt Son whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he ran away, he found no hope of pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, til he called heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth to witneſſe his great iniquitie. Paul who preached the gospell to vs Gentils, how ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doth he confeſſe that he was a perſecutor. The happy thief that was ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ged entred not into paradiſe, til he firſt in the hearing of all Iſraell ſaid, we are rightly puniſhed, &amp; receiue things worthy of that we haue done.
<pb facs="tcp:178438:32"/> What ſhould J ſay more, J truſt you feare God, and J haue ſeene in you many ſignes of grace: I doubt not but you will make it knowen whatſoeuer is in your hart. It is the word of God that I haue ſpoken, &amp; it is the onely trueth vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> which you may build your faith. This thing toucheth ſo neare the glory of God &amp; the ſafetie of his goſpell, that you muſt now needs forſake your friends &amp; kinſme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yea forget the loue of your ſelfe: and if you haue bin partaker of any counſell, diſcloſe the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>spiracies of the wicked: you haue ſtood in iudgement not before me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; for they are but miniſters, but before the Lord, who ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in the middst of iudgement. Surely if you ſeeke to hide your ſins, you ſeeke to hide them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> him that kno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weth the ſecrets of the hart &amp; raynes, and to diſſemble with him that will not be mocked: and therefore with all humblenes of dutie, I beſeech you, &amp; in the name of God J craue this at your hands, vnburthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your own co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, make your hart glad, caſt of the burthe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of your ſecret ſinns, purge the eyes of your minde, that you may ſee Chriſt, let true repe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tance breake forth in holy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, ſhame the Lords enimies, &amp; make the church of God reioyce, and loe in the name of Christ J tell it you Bleſſed is the day in which it was ſaid of you, a man-child is borne, and bleſſed ſhalbe the houre in which it ſhalbe ſaid of you, you are dead in the Lord: the cloſing vp of your eyes ſhalbe the beginning of your ſight: and death your entrance into life. And now my Lord, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you pray for me, &amp; humbly vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> my knees I aſke you hartie forgiuenes wherein I haue not done as it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came me touching you. You knowe howe in my time I haue perſuaded you fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your wicked ſeruants, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your popiſh frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds, &amp; fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your adulterous woman. But (alas)
<pb facs="tcp:178438:32"/> my Lord, your high calling hath bridled my words, I could not ſpeak as I ſhold, my words wer to ſoft to heale ſo old a diſeaſe: why ſhould I haue taried in your lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips houſe, except theſe things had bin ame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded? this bea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ring with your euill, was the greateſt euill I could haue done you. And I beſeech you forgiue me, &amp; God for his mercies ſake ſhall make me ſtrong, that herafter J ſhall not feare to reproue the ſinner, &amp; God ſhall forgiue you your dulnes of ſpirit, that could not be moued with a li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſel. Now my Lord, be ſtrong in the Lord, &amp; feare not, if you muſt dye, reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber that Chriſt bath ouercome him that hath the power of death, &amp; hath ſet vs free fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the power of the graue. Though you doe for a very litle time turne again vnto duſt, yet again you ſhal heare the voyce of the trumpet: corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſhall die, becauſe he was no better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his fathers: &amp; you whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you go, you ſhall go to your fathers, the long race of Nobilitie of which God hath raiſed you, euery one in his time is gone before you, &amp; ſo many as haue died in the faith, they ſhalbe againe of your fellowſhip &amp; kindred, and you ſhall prayſe God with the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; not feare the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d death. The lord ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> your eyes that you may ſee your hope, &amp; you ſhall loue that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany aboue Kings &amp; Princes. You ſhall ſee Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, of who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> you haue heard ſo much, Jſaac, Iacob, Iob, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muell &amp; Daniell, whoſe names you loued, you ſhall ſee Paule &amp; Peter, whoſe ſociety you wiſh for, all the Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, Prophets and Apoſtles that are gone before you. Be bold therfore, &amp; be bold to dye: with Elias you ſhall ſee Chriſt clothed with your fleſh, who hath immorta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>e in his hande, &amp; ſhal make you raigne for euer: yo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſhall not be tedious, and your glory ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> change: &amp; he that made the heauens ſo high abo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:178438:33"/> earth, the Sun the moone the ſtarres, ſo ful of excelle<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t beauty, he ſhalbe your portio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in his endles glory: wold God you cold ſee him now with ope<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tenance, that you might knowe his louing kindnes, how much it is better the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life: J wold you cold withal his ſaints perceue what wer the height, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reath<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the lenght &amp; the depth of his vnſearchable riches. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>apy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſhal neuer end, ô bleſed inherita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce that ſhal neuer waſt O holy citty new Ieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of beauty; where the inhabita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are princes, O'pretious buildng that is not made with hands, &amp; ioyfull tabernacles which God himſelfe hath pitched: my voice faileth &amp; my tonge cleaueh to my mouth whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I wold declare the euerlaſting gladneſſe, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God ſhal wipe away al teares fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> our eies, &amp; ther ſhalbe no more death nether ſorow, nor crying, nor yet any paine for the firſt things paſt. Who reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>breth this &amp; ſaith not, all fleſh is graſſe, and the glory of man is as the flower of the fielde. We haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing here, but feare of our enimie, griefe in pouertie, paine in labour, care in ritches, vnſtedfaſtnes in frindſhip, enuy in authoritie, emulation in honor, change in nobilitie, feare in a kingdome: &amp; as the greateſt of al princes hath wiſely pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced, vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of ſpirit in al things that is vnder the Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, ſo true it is vanity of vanities &amp; al is but vanity. You need no example O my Lord &amp; Maiſter, behold your ſelfe &amp; ſee what you were: reioice in the lord &amp; loue better things, ceaſe to eate of this corruptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; deſire Ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>na: drink not of theſe puddels, but goe to the pure water of life, which is cleare as chriſtal, &amp; procedeth out of the throne of god &amp; of the la<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>be: you are but one ſtep fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this glorious bleſſing, &amp; that is to die willingly &amp; well: ſpeak forth the ſecrets of your hart, &amp; giu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> God glorie The Lord bleſſe &amp; kepe you, the Lord make his face to ſhine vpon you and be mercifull vnto you, the Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ft vp his countenance vpon you and ſende you peace.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:178438:33"/>
            <head>MAISTER DERINGS WORKES.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>LO heere the Pearle of precious price</l>
               <l>From Deringe dead that liues againe</l>
               <l>To preache in print and giue aduice</l>
               <l>Of that he taught in life with payne</l>
               <l>Lo nowe he liues both heere and there</l>
               <l>Whoſe life his foes could hardly beare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Reade then to learne and putte in vre</l>
               <l>And taſte the ſweeteneſſe of his vayne</l>
               <l>So ſhall you ſee an heauenlie lure</l>
               <l>That drawes you vp from th'earth amaine</l>
               <l>And ſhewes the way that leads to life</l>
               <l>And eke the reſt that endes all ſtrife.</l>
            </lg>
            <p>Studie to be approued to the Lord, for if hee alowe not our doinges, though all the world be with vs, it ſhall bringe vs no comfort: and this is our reioycinge, the teſtimonie of a good conſcience.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
